<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Programming | In Pursuit of Laziness]]></title>
  <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-12-13T18:26:04+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://manishearth.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Manish Goregaokar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Converting a WebGL Application to WebVR]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2018/09/11/converting-a-webgl-application-to-webvr/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2018/09/11/converting-a-webgl-application-to-webvr</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote a post for Mozilla Hacks on converting WebGL applications to WebVR,
<a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2018/09/converting-a-webgl-application-to-webvr/">you can read it there</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Enjoy Blogging]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2018/08/26/why-i-enjoy-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2018/08/26/why-i-enjoy-blogging</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>See also: <a href="https://myrrlyn.net/blog/misc/to-all-the-posts-ive-blogged-before">Alex&rsquo;s version of this blog post</a></em></p>

<p>I started this blog three years ago, moving from my <a href="http://inpursuitoflaziness.blogspot.com/">older blog</a>, hoping to written about programming, math, physics, books, and miscellenia. I&rsquo;ve not quite written about everything I wanted to, but I&rsquo;ve been very very happy with the experience of blogging. <code>wc</code> says I&rsquo;ve written almost 75k words, which is mind-boggling to me!</p>

<p>I often get asked by others &mdash; usually trying to decide if they should start blogging &mdash; what it&rsquo;s like. I also often try to convince friends to blog by enumerating why I think it&rsquo;s awesome. Might as well write it down so that it&rsquo;s generally useful for everyone! 😃</p>

<h2>Blogging helps cement my understanding of things!</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve often noticed that I&rsquo;ll start blogging about something I <em>think</em> I understand, and it turns out that my understanding of the subject was somewhat nebulous. Turns out it&rsquo;s pretty easy to convince ourselves that we understand something.</p>

<p>The act of writing stuff down helps cement my own understanding &mdash; words are usually not as nebulous as thoughts so I&rsquo;m forced to figure out little details.</p>

<p>I recall when I wrote my post on <a href="https://manishearth.github.io/blog/2015/05/30/how-rust-achieves-thread-safety/">how Rust&rsquo;s thread safety guarantees work</a>, I <em>thought</em> I understood <code>Send</code> and <code>Sync</code> in Rust. I understood what they did, but I didn&rsquo;t have a clear mental model for them. I obtained this mental model through the process of writing the post; to be able to explain it to others I had to first explain it to myself.</p>

<p>I point out this post in particular because this was both one of the first posts for me where I&rsquo;d noticed this, and, more importantly, my more concrete mental model led to me <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/issues/25894">finding a soundness bug in Rust&rsquo;s standard library</a>. When I was thinking about my mental model I realized &ldquo;an impl that looks like this should never exist&rdquo;,
so I grepped the source code and found one<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve even noticed a difference between one-on-one explaining and explaining things through blog posts. I <em>love</em> explaining things one-on-one, it&rsquo;s much easier to tailor the explanation to the other person&rsquo;s background,
as well as what they&rsquo;re actually asking for help with. Plus, it&rsquo;s interactive. A <em>lot</em> of my posts are of the &ldquo;okay I get this question a lot I&rsquo;m going to write down the answer so I don&rsquo;t have to repeat myself&rdquo; kind and I&rsquo;ve found that I&rsquo;ve often learned things from these despite having talked about the thing in the article contents multiple times.</p>

<p>I guess it&rsquo;s basically that blogging is inherently one-many &mdash; you&rsquo;re trying to explain to a whole group of people with varied backgrounds &mdash; which means you need to cover all your bases<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> and explain everything together instead of the minimum necessary.</p>

<h2>It&rsquo;s really fun to revisit old posts!</h2>

<p>Okay, I&rsquo;ll admit that I never really write blog posts with this in mind. But when I <em>do</em> reread them, I&rsquo;m usually quite thankful I wrote them!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m a fan of rereading in general, I&rsquo;ve reread most of my favorite books tens of times; I make a yearly pilgrimage to <a href="https://mickens.seas.harvard.edu/wisdom-james-mickens">James Mickens&#8217; website</a>; I reread many of my favorite posts and articles on the internet; and I often reread my <em>own</em> posts from the past.</p>

<p>Sometimes I&rsquo;ll do it because I want a refresher in a topic. Sometimes I&rsquo;ll do it because I&rsquo;m bored. Whatever the reason, it&rsquo;s always been a useful and fun thing to do.</p>

<p>Rereading old posts is a great way to transport myself back to my mindset from when I wrote the post. It&rsquo;s easy to see progress in my understanding of things as well as in my writing. It&rsquo;s interesting to note what I thought super important to include in the post <em>then</em> that I consider totally obvious <em>now</em><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. It&rsquo;s interesting to relearn what I&rsquo;ve forgotten. It&rsquo;s reassuring to realize that my terrible jokes were just as terrible as they are now.</p>

<p>One of my favorite posts to reread is <a href="https://manishearth.github.io/blog/2016/03/05/exploring-zero-knowledge-proofs/">this really long one on generalized zero knowledge proofs</a>. It&rsquo;s the longest post I&rsquo;ve written so far<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>, and it&rsquo;s on a topic I don&rsquo;t deal with often &mdash; cryptography. Not only does it help put me back in a mindset for thinking about cryptography, it&rsquo;s about something super interesting but also complicated enough that rereading the post is like learning it all over again.</p>

<h2>It lets me exercise a different headspace!</h2>

<p>I like programming a lot, but if programming was <em>all</em> I did, I&rsquo;d get tired pretty quickly. When I was a student learning physics I&rsquo;d often contribute to open source in my spare time, but now I write code full time so I&rsquo;m less inclined to do it in my free time<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>.</p>

<p>But I still sometimes feel like doing programmery things in my spare time just &hellip; not programming.</p>

<p>Turns out that blogging doesn&rsquo;t tire me out the same way! I&rsquo;m sure that if I spent the whole day writing I&rsquo;d not want to write when I go home, but I don&rsquo;t spend the whole day writing, so it&rsquo;s all good. It&rsquo;s refreshing to sit down to write a blog post and discover a fresh reserve of energy. I&rsquo;m not sure if this is the right term, but I usually call this &ldquo;using a different headspace&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also started using this to plan my work, I mix up the kinds of headspace I&rsquo;m employing for various tasks so that I feel energetic throughout the day.</p>

<p>This is also why I really enjoy mentoring &mdash; mentoring often requires the same effort from me as fixing it myself, but it&rsquo;s a different headspace I&rsquo;m employing so it&rsquo;s less tiring.</p>

<h2>Blogging lets me be lazy!</h2>

<p>I often find myself explaining things often. I like helping folks and explaining things, but I&rsquo;m also lazy<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, so writing stuff down really makes stuff easy for me! If folks ask me a question I can give a quick answer and then go &ldquo;if you want to learn more, I&rsquo;ve written about it here!&rdquo;. If folks are asking a question a lot, there&rsquo;s probably something missing in the documentation or learning materials about it. Some things can be fixed upstream in documentation, but other things &mdash; like <a href="https://manishearth.github.io/blog/2017/05/14/mentally-modelling-modules/">&ldquo;how should I reason about modules in Rust?&rdquo;</a> deserve to be tackled as a separate problem and addressed with their own post.</p>

<p>(Yes, this post is in this category!)</p>

<h2>It&rsquo;s okay if folks have written about it before!</h2>

<p>A common question I&rsquo;ve gotten is &ldquo;Well I can write about X but &hellip; there are a lot of other posts out there about it, should I still?&rdquo;</p>

<p>Yes!!</p>

<p>People think differently, people learn differently, and people come from different backgrounds. Existing posts may be useful for some folks but less useful for others.</p>

<p>My personal rule of thumb is that if it took <em>me</em> some effort to understand something after reading about it, that&rsquo;s something worth writing about, so it&rsquo;s easier to understand for others like me encountering the subject.</p>

<p>One of my favorite bloggers, <a href="https://jvns.ca/">Julia Evans</a> very often writes posts explaining computer concepts. Most of the times these have been explained before in other blog posts or manuals. But that doesn&rsquo;t matter &mdash; her posts are <em>different</em>, and they&rsquo;re <em>amazing</em>. They&rsquo;re upbeat, fun to read, and often get me excited to learn more about things I knew about but never really looked at closely before.</p>

<h2>I kinda feel it&rsquo;s my duty to?</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s a quote by Toni Morrison I quite enjoy:</p>

<blockquote><p>I tell my students, &lsquo;When you get these jobs that you have been so brilliantly trained for, just remember that your real job is that if you are free, you need to free somebody else. If you have some power, then your job is to empower somebody else. This is not just a grab-bag candy game.</p></blockquote>

<p>I enjoy it so much I <a href="https://manishearth.github.io/rustfest-slides/#/13">concluded my talk at RustFest Kyiv with it</a>!</p>

<p>I have the privilege of having time to do things like blogging and mentoring. Given that, I feel that it really is my duty to share what I know as much as possible; to help others attempting to tread the path I&rsquo;m treading; and to battle against tribal knowledge.</p>

<p>When it comes to programming I&rsquo;m mostly &ldquo;self-taught&rdquo;. But when I say that, I really mean that I wasn&rsquo;t taught in a traditional way by other humans &mdash; I learned things by trying stuff out and <em>reading what others had written</em>. I didn&rsquo;t learn Rust by taking <code>rustc</code> and pretending to be a fuzzer and just trying random nonsense till stuff made sense, I went through the tutorial (and <em>then</em> started exploring by trying random stuff). I didn&rsquo;t figure out cool algorithms by discovering them from first principles, I picked them up from books and blog posts. I&rsquo;m &ldquo;self-taught&rdquo; because I&rsquo;ve been in charge of my learning process, but I&rsquo;ve definitely relied on the work of other people throughout this process.</p>

<p>This means that for me, personally, knowledge-sharing is especially important. If I had to spend time figuring something out, I should make it easier for the next people to try<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup>.</p>

<p>(All this said, I probably don&rsquo;t blog as much as I <em>should</em>)</p>

<h2>You should blog too!</h2>

<p>I wish everyone wrote more. I know not everyone has the time/privilege to do this, but if you do, I urge you to start!</p>

<p>I feel like tips on <em>how</em> to blog would fill up an entire other blog post, but Julia Evans has <a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2016/05/22/how-do-you-write-blog-posts//">multiple</a> <a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2017/03/20/blogging-principles/">posts</a> on this that I strongly recommend. Feel free to ask me for review on posts!</p>

<p>As for the technicalities of setting up a blog, my colleague Emily recently <a href="https://www.emilykager.com/writing/2018/07/27/myo-website.html">wrote a great post about doing this with Jekyll</a>. This blog uses <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> which is similar to set up.</p>

<p><em>Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/arshia__">Arshia</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/QuietMisdreavus">QuietMisdreavus</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/myrrlyn">Alex</a> for reviewing drafts of this blog post.</em></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Who needs to <a href="https://www.ralfj.de/blog/2017/06/09/mutexguard-sync.html">look for unsoundness with rigorous formal verification</a> when you have <code>grep</code>?<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Incidentally, I find there&rsquo;s a similar dynamic when it comes to forum discussions vs hashing things out one-on-one, it&rsquo;s way harder to get anywhere with forum discussions because they&rsquo;re one-many and you have to put in that much more work to empathize with everyone else and also phrase things in a way that is resilient to accidental misinterpretation.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>This is especially important as I get more and more &ldquo;used&rdquo; to subjects I&rsquo;m familiar with &ndash; it&rsquo;s easy to lose the ability to explain things when I think half of it is obvious.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>This is probably the <em>real</em> reason I love rereading it &mdash; I like being verbose and would nest parentheses and footnotes if society let me<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>I also am in general less inclined to do technical things in my free time and have a better work-life balance, glad that worked out!<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>See blog title<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>One of my former title ideas for this post was &ldquo;Knowledge is Theft&rdquo;, riffing off of this concept, but I felt that was a bit too tongue-in-cheek.<a href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Down a Rusty Rabbit Hole]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2018/04/12/down-a-rusty-rabbit-hole/"/>
    <updated>2018-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2018/04/12/down-a-rusty-rabbit-hole</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I fell down a rather interesting rabbit hole in Rust, which was basically
me discovering a series of quirks of the Rust compiler/language, each one leading to the
next when I asked &ldquo;why?&rdquo;.</p>

<p>It started when someone asked why autogenerated <code>Debug</code> impls use argument names like <code>__arg_0</code>
which start with a double underscore.</p>

<p>This happened to be <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/pull/32294">my fault</a>. The reason <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/pull/32251#issuecomment-197481726">we used a double underscore</a> was that
while a single underscore tells rustc not to warn about a possibly-unused variable, there&rsquo;s an off-
by-default clippy lint that warns about variables that start with a single underscore that are used,
which can be silenced with a double underscore. Now, the correct fix here is to make the lint ignore
derive/macros (which I believe we did as well), but at the time we needed to add an underscore
anyway so a double underscore didn&rsquo;t seem worse.</p>

<p>Except of course, this double underscore appears in the docs. Oops.</p>

<p>Ideally the rustc derive infrastructure would have a way of specifying the argument name to use so
that we can at least have descriptive things here, but that&rsquo;s a bit more work (I&rsquo;m willing to mentor
this work though!). So I thought I&rsquo;d fix this by at least removing the double underscore, and making
the unused lint ignore <code>#[derive()]</code> output.</p>

<p>While going through the code to look for underscores I also discovered a hygiene issue. The following code
throws a bunch of very weird type errors:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">pub const __cmp: u8 = 1;

#[derive(PartialOrd, PartialEq)]
pub enum Foo {
    A(u8), B(u8)
}
</code></pre>

<p>(<a href="https://play.rust-lang.org/?gist=2352b6a2192f38caba70bc2b1fa889e7&amp;version=stable">playpen</a>)</p>

<pre><code>error[E0308]: mismatched types
 --&gt; src/main.rs:6:7
  |
6 |     A(u8), B(u8)
  |       ^^^ expected enum `std::option::Option`, found u8
  |
  = note: expected type `std::option::Option&lt;std::cmp::Ordering&gt;`
             found type `u8`
.....
</code></pre>

<p>This is because the generated code for PartialOrd contains the following:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">match foo.cmp(bar) {
    Some(Ordering::Equal) =&gt; .....,
    __cmp =&gt; __cmp,
}
</code></pre>

<p><code>__cmp</code> can both be a binding to a wildcard pattern match as well as a match against a constant
named <code>__cmp</code>, and in the presence of such a constant it resolves to the constant, causing
type errors.</p>

<p>One way to fix this is to bind <code>foo.cmp(bar)</code> to some temporary variable <code>x</code> and use that directly in
a <code>_ =&gt; x</code> branch.</p>

<p>I thought I could be clever and try <code>cmp @ _ =&gt; cmp</code> instead. <code>match</code> supports syntax where you can
do <code>foo @ &lt;pattern&gt;</code>, where <code>foo</code> is bound to the entire matched variable. The <code>cmp</code> here is unambiguously
a binding; it cannot be a pattern. So no conflicting with the <code>const</code>, problem solved!</p>

<p>So I made <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/pull/49676">a PR for both removing the underscores and also fixing this</a>. The change for <code>__cmp</code>
is no longer in that PR, but you can find it <a href="https://github.com/Manishearth/rust/commit/partial-cmp-hygiene">here</a>.</p>

<p>Except I hit a problem. With that PR, the following still breaks:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">pub const cmp: u8 = 1;

#[derive(PartialOrd, PartialEq)]
pub enum Foo {
    A(u8), B(u8)
}
</code></pre>

<p>throwing a slightly cryptic error:</p>

<pre><code>error[E0530]: match bindings cannot shadow constants
 --&gt; test.rs:9:7
  |
4 | pub const cmp: u8 = 1;
  | ---------------------- a constant `cmp` is defined here
...
9 |     B(u8)
  |       ^^^ cannot be named the same as a constant
</code></pre>

<p>You can see a reduced version of this error in the following code:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">pub const cmp : u8 = 1;

fn main() {
    match 1 {
        cmp @ _ =&gt; ()
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>(<a href="https://play.rust-lang.org/?gist=feebbc048b47c286d5720b9926c6925e&amp;version=stable">playpen</a>)</p>

<p>Huh. Wat. Why? <code>cmp @ _</code> seems to be pretty unambiguous, what&rsquo;s wrong with it shadowing a constant?</p>

<p>Turns out bindings cannot shadow constants at all, for a <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/issues/33118#issuecomment-233962221">rather subtle reason</a>:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">const A: u8 = ...; // A_const
let A @ _ = ...; // A_let
match .. {
    A =&gt; ...; // A_match
}
</code></pre>

<p>What happens here is that constants and variables occupy the same namespace. So <code>A_let</code> shadows
<code>A_const</code> here, and when we attempt to <code>match</code>, <code>A_match</code> is resolved to <code>A_let</code> and rejected (since
you can&rsquo;t match against a variable), and <code>A_match</code> falls back to resolving as a fresh binding
pattern, instead of resolving to a pattern that matches against <code>A_const</code>.</p>

<p>This is kinda weird, so we disallow shadowing constants with variables. This is rarely a problem
because variables are lowercase and constants are uppercase. We could <em>technically</em> allow this
language-wise, but it&rsquo;s hard on the implementation (and irrelevant in practice) so we don&rsquo;t.</p>

<hr />

<p>So I dropped that fix. The temporary local variable approach is broken as well since
you can also name a constant the same as the local variable and have a clash (so again, you
need the underscores to avoid surprises).</p>

<p>But then I realized that we had an issue with removing the underscores from <code>__arg_0</code> as well.</p>

<p>The following code is also broken:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">pub const __arg_0: u8 = 1;

#[derive(Debug)]
struct Foo(u8);
</code></pre>

<p>(<a href="https://play.rust-lang.org/?gist=6e10fd8de1123c6f6f695c891e879f70&amp;version=stable">playpen</a>)</p>

<pre><code>error[E0308]: mismatched types
 --&gt; src/main.rs:3:10
  |
3 | #[derive(Debug)]
  |          ^^^^^ expected mutable reference, found u8
  |
  = note: expected type `&amp;mut std::fmt::Formatter&lt;'_&gt;`
             found type `u8`
</code></pre>

<p>You can see a reduced version of this error in the following code:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">pub const __arg_0: u8 = 1;

fn foo(__arg_0: bool) {}
</code></pre>

<pre><code>error[E0308]: mismatched types
 --&gt; src/main.rs:3:8
  |
3 | fn foo(__arg_0: bool) {}
  |        ^^^^^^^ expected bool, found u8
</code></pre>

<p>(<a href="https://play.rust-lang.org/?gist=2cf2c8b3520d5b343de1b76f80ea3fe7&amp;version=stable">playpen</a>)</p>

<p>This breakage is not an issue with the current code because of the double underscores &ndash; there&rsquo;s a
very low chance someone will create a constant that is both lowercase and starts with a double
underscore. But it&rsquo;s a problem when I remove the underscores since that chance shoots up.</p>

<p>Anyway, this failure is even weirder. Why are we attempting to match against the constant in the
first place? <code>fn</code> argument patterns<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> are irrefutable, i.e. all possible values of the type should match
the argument. For example, <code>fn foo(Some(foo): Option&lt;u8&gt;) {}</code> will fail to compile with
&ldquo;refutable pattern in function argument: <code>None</code> not covered&rdquo;.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no point trying to match against constants here; because even if we find a constant it will be rejected
later. Instead, we can unambiguously resolve identifiers as new bindings, yes?</p>

<p>Right?</p>

<p>Firm in my belief, <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/issues/49680">I filed an issue</a>.</p>

<p>I was wrong, it&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/issues/49680#issuecomment-379029404">not going to always be rejected later</a>. With zero-sized types this
can totally still work:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">struct S;

const C: S = S;

fn main() {
    let C = S;
}
</code></pre>

<p>Here because <code>S</code> has only one state, matching against a constant of the type is still irrefutable.</p>

<p>I argued that this doesn&rsquo;t matter &ndash; since the type has a single value, it doesn&rsquo;t matter whether we resolved to
a new binding or the constant; the value and semantics are the same.</p>

<p>This is true.</p>

<p>Except.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/issues/49680#issuecomment-379032842">Except for when destructors come in</a>.</p>

<p>It was at this point that my table found itself in the perplexing state of being upside-down.</p>

<p>This is still really fine, zero-sized-constants-with-destructors is a pretty rare thing in Rust
and I don&rsquo;t really see folks <em>relying</em> on this behavior.</p>

<p>However I later realized that this entire detour was pointless because even if we fix this, we end up
with a way for bindings to shadow constants. Which &hellip; which we already realized isn&rsquo;t allowed by the
compiler till we fix some bugs.</p>

<p>Damn.</p>

<hr />

<p>The <em>actual</em> fix to the macro stuff is to use hygenic generated variable names, which the current
infrastructure supports. I plan to make a PR for this eventually.</p>

<p>But it was a very interesting dive into the nuances of pattern matching in Rust.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Yes, function arguments in Rust are patterns. You can totally do things like <code>(a, b): (u8, u8)</code> in function arguments (like you can do in <code>let</code>)<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Picking Apart the Crashing iOS String]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2018/02/15/picking-apart-the-crashing-ios-string/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2018/02/15/picking-apart-the-crashing-ios-string</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So there&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/2/15/17015654/apple-iphone-crash-ios-11-bug-imessage">yet another iOS text crash</a>, where just looking at a particular string crashes
iOS. Basically, if you put this string in any system text box (and other places), it crashes that
process. I&rsquo;ve been testing it by copy-pasting characters into Spotlight so I don&rsquo;t end up crashing
my browser.</p>

<p>The original sequence is U+0C1C U+0C4D U+0C1E U+200C U+0C3E, which is a sequence of Telugu
characters: the consonant ja (జ), a virama (&#8239;్&#8239;), the consonant nya (ఞ), a zero-width non-joiner, and
the vowel aa (&#8239;ా).</p>

<p>I was pretty interested in what made this sequence &ldquo;special&rdquo;, and started investigating.</p>

<p>So first when looking into this, I thought that the &lt;ja, virama, nya&gt; sequence was the culprit.
That sequence forms a special ligature in many Indic scripts (ज्ञ in Devanagari) which is often
considered a letter of its own. However, the ligature for Telugu doesn&rsquo;t seem very &ldquo;special&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Also, from some experimentation, this bug seemed to occur for <em>any</em> pair of Telugu consonants with
a vowel, as long as the vowel is not &nbsp;&#8239;ై (ai). Huh.</p>

<p>The ZWNJ must be doing something weird, then. &lt;consonant, virama, consonant, vowel&gt; is a
pretty common sequence in any Indic script; but ZWNJ before a vowel isn&rsquo;t very useful for most
scripts (except for Bengali and Oriya, but I&rsquo;ll get to that).</p>

<p>And then I saw that <a href="https://twitter.com/FakeUnicode/status/963300865762254848">there was a sequence in Bengali</a> that also crashed.</p>

<p>The sequence is U+09B8 U+09CD U+09B0 U+200C U+09C1, which is the consonant &ldquo;so&rdquo; (স), a virama (&#8239;্&#8239;),
the consonant &ldquo;ro&rdquo; (র), a ZWNJ, and vowel u (&nbsp;&#8239;ু).</p>

<p>Before we get too into this, let&rsquo;s first take a little detour to learn how Indic scripts work:</p>

<h2>Indic scripts and consonant clusters</h2>

<p>Indic scripts are <em>abugidas</em>; which means that their &ldquo;letters&rdquo; are consonants, which you
can attach diacritics to to change the vowel. By default, consonants have a base vowel.
So, for example, क is &ldquo;kuh&rdquo; (kə, often transcribed as &ldquo;ka&rdquo;), but I can change the vowel to make it के
(the &ldquo;ka&rdquo; in &ldquo;okay&rdquo;) का (&ldquo;kaa&rdquo;, like &ldquo;car&rdquo;).</p>

<p>Usually, the default vowel is the ə sound, though not always (in Bengali it&rsquo;s more of an o sound).</p>

<p>Because of the &ldquo;default&rdquo; vowel, you need a way to combine consonants. For example, if you wished to
write the word &ldquo;ski&rdquo;, you can&rsquo;t write it as स + की (sa + ki = &ldquo;saki&rdquo;), you must write it as स्की.
What&rsquo;s happened here is that the स got its vowel &ldquo;killed&rdquo;, and got tacked on to the की to form a
consonant cluster ligature.</p>

<p>You can <em>also</em> write this as स्&zwnj;की . That little tail you see on the स is known as a &ldquo;virama&rdquo;;
it basically means &ldquo;remove this vowel&rdquo;. Explicit viramas are sometimes used when there&rsquo;s no easy way
to form a ligature, e.g. in ङ्&zwnj;ठ because there is no simple way to ligatureify ङ into ठ. Some scripts
also <em>prefer</em> explicit viramas, e.g. &ldquo;ski&rdquo; in Malayalam is written as സ്കീ, where the little crescent
is the explicit virama.</p>

<p>In unicode, the virama character is always used to form a consonant cluster. So स्की was written as
&lt;स, &#8239;्, क, &#8239;ी&gt;, or &lt;sa, virama, ka, i&gt;. If the font supports the cluster, it will show up
as a ligature, otherwise it will use an explicit virama.</p>

<p>For Devanagari and Bengali, <em>usually</em>, in a consonant cluster the first consonant is munged a bit and the second consonant stays intact.
There are exceptions &ndash; sometimes they&rsquo;ll form an entirely new glyph (क + ष = क्ष), and sometimes both
glyphs will change (ड + ड = ड्ड, द + म = द्म, द + ब = द्ब). Those last ones should look like this in conjunct form:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/post/unicode-crash/conjuncts.png" width="200"></p>

<h2>Investigating the Bengali case</h2>

<p>Now, interestingly, unlike the Telugu crash, the Bengali crash seemed to only occur when the second
consonant is র (&ldquo;ro&rdquo;). However, I can trigger it for any choice of the first consonant or vowel, except
when the vowel is &#8239;ো (o) or &#8239;ৌ (au).</p>

<p>Now, র is an interesting consonant in some Indic scripts, including Devanagari. In Devanagari,
it looks like र (&ldquo;ra&rdquo;). However, it does all kinds of things when forming a cluster. If you&rsquo;re having it
precede another consonant in a cluster, it forms a little feather-like stroke, like in र्क (rka). In Marathi,
that stroke can also look like a tusk, as in र्&zwj;क. As a suffix consonant, it can provide a little
&ldquo;extra leg&rdquo;, as in क्र (kra). For letters without a vertical stroke, like ठ (tha), it does this caret-like thing,
ठ्र (thra).</p>

<p>Basically, while most consonants retain some of their form when put inside a cluster, र does not. And
a more special thing about र is that this happens even when र is the <em>second</em> consonant in a cluster &ndash; as I mentioned
before, for most consonant clusters the second consonant stays intact. While there are exceptions, they are usually
specific to the cluster; it is only र for which this happens for all clusters.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s similar in Bengali, র as the second consonant adds a tentacle-like thing on the existing consonant. For example,
প + র (po + ro) gives প্র (pro).</p>

<p>But it&rsquo;s not just র that does this in Bengali, the consonant &ldquo;jo&rdquo; does as well. প + য (po + jo) forms প্য (pjo),
and the য is transformed into a wavy line called a &ldquo;jophola&rdquo;.</p>

<p>So I tried it with য  &mdash; , and it turns out that the Bengali crash occurs for  য as well!
So the general Bengali case is &lt;consonant, virama, র OR য, ZWNJ, vowel&gt;, where the vowel is not  &#8239;ো or &#8239;ৌ.</p>

<h2>Suffix-joining consonants</h2>

<p>So we&rsquo;re getting close, here. At least for Bengali, it occurs when the second consonant is such that it often
combines with the first consonant without modifying its form much.</p>

<p>In fact, this is the case for Telugu as well! Consonant clusters in Telugu are usually formed by preserving the
original consonant, and tacking the second consonant on below!</p>

<p>For example, the original crashy string contains the cluster జ + ఞ, which looks like జ్ఞ. The first letter isn&rsquo;t
really modified, but the second is.</p>

<p>From this, we can guess that it will also occur for Devanagari with र. Indeed it does! U+0915 U+094D U+0930 U+200C U+093E, that is,
&lt;क, &#8239;्, र, zwnj, &#8239;ा&gt; (&lt; ka, virama, ra, zwnj, aa &gt;) is one such crashing sequence.</p>

<p>But this isn&rsquo;t really the whole story, is it? For example, the crash does occur for &ldquo;kro&rdquo; + zwnj + vowel in Bengali,
and in &ldquo;kro&rdquo; (ক্র = ক + র = ko + ro) the resultant cluster involves the munging of both the prefix and suffix. But
the crash doesn&rsquo;t occur for द्ब or ड्ड. It seems to be specific to the letter, not the nature of the cluster.</p>

<p>Digging deeper, the reason is that for many fonts (presumably the ones in use), these consonants
form &ldquo;suffix joining consonants&rdquo;<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> (a term I made up) when preceded by a virama. This seems to
correspond to the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/typography/opentype/spec/features_pt#tag-pstf"><code>pstf</code> OpenType feature</a>, as well as <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/typography/opentype/spec/features_uz#vatu"><code>vatu</code></a>.</p>

<p>For example, the sequence virama + क gives &nbsp;&#8239;्क, i.e. it renders a virama with a placeholder followed by a क.</p>

<p>But, for र, virama + र renders &#8239;्र, which for me looks like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/post/unicode-crash/virama-ra.png" width="200"></p>

<p>In fact, this is the case for the other consonants as well. For me, &#8239;्र &#8239;্র &#8239;্য &#8239;్ఞ &#8239;్క
(Devanagari virama-ra, Bengali virama-ro, Bengali virama-jo, Telugu virama-nya, Telugu virama-ka)
all render as &ldquo;suffix joining consonants&rdquo;:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/post/unicode-crash/virama-consonant.png" width="200"></p>

<p>(This is true for all Telugu consonants, not just the ones listed).</p>

<p>An interesting bit is that the crash does not occur for &lt;र, virama, र, zwnj, vowel&gt;, because र-virama-र
uses the prefix-joining form of the first र (र्र). The same occurs for র with itself or ৰ or য. Because the virama
is &ldquo;sticker&rdquo; to the left in these cases, it doesn&rsquo;t cause a crash. (h/t <a href="https://github.com/hackbunny">hackbunny</a> for discovering this
using a <a href="https://github.com/hackbunny/viramarama">script</a> to enumerate all cases).</p>

<p>Kannada <em>also</em> has &ldquo;suffix joining consonants&rdquo;, but for some reason I cannot trigger the crash with it. Ya in Gurmukhi
is also suffix-joining.</p>

<h2>The ZWNJ</h2>

<p>The ZWNJ is curious. The crash doesn&rsquo;t happen without it, but as I mentioned before a ZWNJ before a vowel
doesn&rsquo;t really <em>do</em> anything for most Indic scripts. In Indic scripts, a ZWNJ can be used to explicitly force a
virama if used after the virama (I used it to write स्&zwnj;की in this post), however that&rsquo;s not how it&rsquo;s being used here.</p>

<p>In Bengali and Oriya specifically, a ZWNJ can be used to force a different vowel form when used before a vowel
(e.g. রু vs র&zwnj;ু), however this bug seems to apply to vowels for which there is only one form, and this bug
also applies to other scripts where this isn&rsquo;t the case anyway.</p>

<p>The exception vowels are interesting. They&rsquo;re basically all vowels that are made up of <em>two</em> glyph components. Philippe Verdy
points out:</p>

<blockquote><p>And why this bug does not occur with some vowels is because these are vowels in two parts,
that are first decomposed into two separate glyphs reordered in the buffer of glyphs, while
other vowels do not need this prior mapping and keep their initial direct mapping from their
codepoints in fonts, which means that this has to do to the way the ZWNJ looks for the glyphs
of the vowels in the glyphs buffer and not in the initial codepoints buffer: there&rsquo;s some desynchronization,
and more probably an uninitialized data field (for the lookup made in handling ZWNJ) if no vowel decomposition was done
(the same data field is correctly initialized when it is the first consonnant which takes an alternate form before
a virama, like in most Indic consonnant clusters, because the a glyph buffer is created.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Generalizing</h2>

<p>So, ultimately, the full set of cases that cause the crash are:</p>

<p>Any sequence <code>&lt;consonant1, virama, consonant2, ZWNJ, vowel&gt;</code> in Devanagari, Bengali, and Telugu, where:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>consonant2</code> is suffix-joining (<code>pstf</code>/<code>vatu</code>) &ndash; i.e. र, র, য, ৰ, and all Telugu consonants</li>
<li><code>consonant1</code> is not a reph-forming letter like र/র (or a variant, like ৰ)</li>
<li><code>vowel</code> does not have two glyph components, i.e. it is not &nbsp;&#8239;ై, &nbsp;&#8239;ো, or &nbsp;&#8239;ৌ</li>
</ul>


<p>This leaves one question open:</p>

<p>Why doesn&rsquo;t it apply to Kannada? Or, for that matter, Khmer, which has a similar virama-like thing called a &ldquo;coeng&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>Are these valid strings?</h2>

<p>A recurring question I&rsquo;m getting is if these strings are valid in the language, or unicode gibberish
like Zalgo text. Breaking it down:</p>

<ul>
<li>All of the <em>rendered</em> glyphs are valid. The original Telugu one is the root of the word for
&ldquo;knowledge&rdquo; (and I&rsquo;ve taken to calling this bug &ldquo;forbidden knowledge&rdquo; for that reason).</li>
<li>In Telugu and Devanagari, there is no functional use of the ZWNJ as used before a vowel. It
should not be there, and one would not expect it in typical text.</li>
<li>In Bengali (also Oriya), putting a ZWNJ before some vowels prevents them from ligatureifying, and this is
mentioned in the Unicode spec. However, it seems rare for native speakers to use this.</li>
<li>In all of these scripts, putting a ZWNJ after viramas can be used to force an explicit virama
over a ligature. That is not the position ZWNJ is used here, but it gives a hint that this
might have been a mistype. Doing this is <em>also</em> rare at least for Devanagari (and I believe
for the other two scripts as well)</li>
<li>Android has an explicit key for ZWNJ on its keyboards for these languages<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, right next to the spacebar. iOS has this as
well on the long-press of the virama key. <em>Very</em> easy to mistype, at least for Android.</li>
</ul>


<p>So while the crashing strings are usually invalid, and when not, very rare, they are easy enough to mistype.</p>

<p>An example by <a href="https://twitter.com/FakeUnicode">@FakeUnicode</a> was the string &ldquo;For/k&rdquo; (or &ldquo;Foŕk&rdquo;, if accents were easier to type). A
slash isn&rsquo;t something you&rsquo;d normally type there, and the produced string is gibberish, but it&rsquo;s easy enough to type
by accident.</p>

<p>Except of course that the mistake in &ldquo;For/k&rdquo;/&ldquo;Foŕk&rdquo; is visually obvious and would be fixed; this
isn&rsquo;t the case for most of the crashing strings.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t really have <em>one</em> guess as to what&rsquo;s going on here &ndash; I&rsquo;d love to see what people think &ndash; but my current
guess is that the &ldquo;affinity&rdquo; of the virama to the left instead of the right confuses the algorithm that handles ZWNJs after
viramas into thinking the ZWNJ applies to the virama (it doesn&rsquo;t, there&rsquo;s a consonant in between), and this leads to some numbers
not matching up and causing a buffer overflow or something. Philippe&rsquo;s diagnosis of the vowel situation matches up with this.</p>

<p>An interesting thing is that I can cause this crash to happen more reliably in browsers by clicking on the string.</p>

<p>Additionally, <em>sometimes</em> it actually renders in spotlight for a split second before crashing; which
means that either the crash isn&rsquo;t deterministic, or it occurs in some process <em>after</em> rendering. I&rsquo;m
not sure what to think of either. Looking at the backtraces, the crash seems to occur in different
places, so it&rsquo;s likely that it&rsquo;s memory corruption that gets uncovered later.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d love to hear if folks have further insight into this.</p>

<p>Update: Philippe on the Unicode mailing list has <a href="https://www.unicode.org/mail-arch/unicode-ml/y2018-m02/0103.html">an interesting theory</a></p>

<p><small>Yes, I could attach a debugger to the crashing process and investigate that instead, but that&rsquo;s no fun 😂</small></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Philippe Verdy points out that these may be called &ldquo;phala forms&rdquo; at least for Bengali<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>I don&rsquo;t think the Android keyboard <em>needs</em> this key; the keyboard seems very much a dump of &ldquo;what does this unicode block let us do&rdquo;, and includes things like Sindhi-specific or Kashmiri-specific characters for the Marathi keyboard as well as <em>extremely</em> archaic characters, whilst neglecting more common things like the eyelash reph (which doesn&rsquo;t have its own code point but is a special unicode sequence; native speakers should not be expected to be aware of this sequence).<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Rough Proposal for Sum Types in Go]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2018/02/01/a-rough-proposal-for-sum-types-in-go/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2018/02/01/a-rough-proposal-for-sum-types-in-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sum types are pretty cool. Just like how a struct is basically &ldquo;This contains one of these <em>and</em> one of these&rdquo;,
a sum type is &ldquo;This contains one of these <em>or</em> one of these&rdquo;.</p>

<p>So for example, the following sum type in Rust:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">enum Foo {
    Stringy(String),
    Numerical(u32)
}
</code></pre>

<p>or Swift:</p>

<pre><code class="swift">enum Foo {
    case stringy(String),
    case numerical(Int)
}
</code></pre>

<p>would be one where it&rsquo;s either <code>Foo::Stringy</code> (<code>Foo::stringy</code> for swift), containing a <code>String</code>,
<em>or</em> <code>Foo::Numerical</code>, containing an integer.</p>

<p>This can be pretty useful. For example, messages between threads are often of a &ldquo;this or that or that or that&rdquo;
form.</p>

<p>The nice thing is, matching (switching) on these enums is usually <em>exhaustive</em> &ndash; you must list all
the cases (or include a default arm) for your code to compile. This leads to a useful component
of type safety &ndash; if you add a message to your message passing system, you&rsquo;ll know where to update it.</p>

<p>Go doesn&rsquo;t have these. Go <em>does</em> have interfaces, which are dynamically dispatched. The drawback here
is that you do not get the exhaustiveness condition, and consumers of your library can even add further
cases. (And, of course, dynamic dispatch can be slow). You <em>can</em> get exhaustiveness in Go with <a href="https://github.com/haya14busa/gosum">external tools</a>,
but it&rsquo;s preferable to have such things in the language IMO.</p>

<p>Many years ago when I was learning Go I wrote a <a href="http://inpursuitoflaziness.blogspot.in/2015/02/thoughts-of-rustacean-learning-go.html">blog post</a> about what I liked and disliked
as a Rustacean learning Go. Since then, I&rsquo;ve spent a lot more time with Go, and I&rsquo;ve learned to like each Go design decision that I initially
disliked, <em>except</em> for the lack of sum types. Most of my issues arose from &ldquo;trying to program Rust in Go&rdquo;,
i.e. using idioms that are natural to Rust (or other languages I&rsquo;d used previously). Once I got used to the
programming style, I realized that aside from the lack of sum types I really didn&rsquo;t find much missing
from the language. Perhaps improvements to error handling.</p>

<p>Now, my intention here isn&rsquo;t really to sell sum types. They&rsquo;re somewhat controversial for Go, and
there are good arguments on both sides. You can see one discussion on this topic <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/issues/19412">here</a>.
If I were to make a more concrete proposal I&rsquo;d probably try to motivate this in much more depth. But even
I&rsquo;m not very <em>strongly</em> of the opinion that Go needs sum types; I have a slight preference for it.</p>

<p>Instead, I&rsquo;m going to try and sketch this proposal for sum types that has been floating around my
mind for a while. I end up mentioning it often and it&rsquo;s nice to have something to link to. Overall,
I think this &ldquo;fits well&rdquo; with the existing Go language design.</p>

<h2>The proposal</h2>

<p>The essence is pretty straightforward: Extend interfaces to allow for &ldquo;closed interfaces&rdquo;. These are
interfaces that are only implemented for a small list of types.</p>

<p>Writing the <code>Foo</code> sum type above would be:</p>

<pre><code class="go">type Foo interface {
    SomeFunction()
    OtherFunction()
    for string, int
}
</code></pre>

<p>It doesn&rsquo;t even need to have functions defined on it.</p>

<p>The interface functions can only be called if you have an interface object; they are not directly available
on variant types without explicitly casting (<code>Foo("...").SomeFunction()</code>).</p>

<p>(I&rsquo;m not strongly for the <code>for</code> keyword syntax, it&rsquo;s just a suggestion. The core idea is that
you define an interface and you define the types it closes over. Somehow.)</p>

<p>A better example would be an interface for a message-passing system for Raft:</p>

<pre><code class="go">type VoteRequest struct {
    CandidateId uint
    Term uint
    // ...
}

type VoteResponse struct {
    Term uint
    VoteGranted bool
    VoterId uint
}

type AppendRequest struct {
    //...
}

type AppendResponse struct {
    //...
}
// ...
type RaftMessage interface {
    for VoteRequest, VoteResponse, AppendRequest, AppendResponse
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, you use type switches for dealing with these:</p>

<pre><code class="go">switch value := msg.(type) {
    case VoteRequest:
        if value.Term &lt;= me.Term {
            me.reject_vote(value.CandidateId)
        } else {
            me.accept_vote(value.CandidateId, value.Term)
        }
    case VoteResponse: // ...
    case AppendRequest: // ...
    case AppendResponse: // ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>There is no need for the default case, unless you wish to leave one or more of the cases out.</p>

<p>Ideally, these could be implemented as inline structs instead of using dynamic dispatch. I&rsquo;m not sure
what this entails for the GC design, but I&rsquo;d love to hear thoughts on this.</p>

<p>We also make it possible to add methods to closed interfaces. This is in the spirit of
<a href="https://github.com/golang/go/issues/16254">this proposal</a>, where you allow</p>

<pre><code class="go">func (message RaftMessage) Process(me Me) error {
    // message handling logic
}
</code></pre>

<p>for closed interfaces.</p>

<p>This aligns more with how sum types are written and used in other languages; instead of assuming
that each method will be a <code>switch</code> on the variant, you can write arbitrary code that <em>may</em> <code>switch</code>
on the type but it can also just call other methods. This is really nice because you can write
methods in <em>both</em> ways &ndash; if it&rsquo;s a &ldquo;responsibility of the inner type&rdquo; kind of method, require it in
the interface and delegate it to the individual types. If it&rsquo;s a &ldquo;responsibility of the interface&rdquo;
method, write it as a method on the interface as a whole. I kind of wish Rust had this, because in Rust
you sometimes end up writing things like:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">match foo {
    Foo::Stringy(s) =&gt; s.process(),
    Foo::Numerical(n) =&gt; n.process(),
    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>Yes, this would work better as a trait, but then you lose some niceties of Rust enums. With this
proposal Go can have it both ways.</p>

<hr />

<p>Anyway, thoughts? This is a really rough proposal, and I&rsquo;m not sure how receptive other Gophers will be
to this, nor how complex its implementation would be. I don&rsquo;t really intend to submit this as a formal proposal,
but if someone else wants to they are more than welcome to build on this idea.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
