<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Programming | In Pursuit of Laziness]]></title>
  <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-21T23:50:54-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://manishearth.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Manish Goregaokar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's Stop Ascribing Meaning to Code Points]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2017/01/14/stop-ascribing-meaning-to-unicode-code-points/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-14T10:13:18-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2017/01/14/stop-ascribing-meaning-to-unicode-code-points</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Update: This post got a sequel, <a href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2017/01/15/breaking-our-latin-1-assumptions/">Breaking our latin-1 assumptions</a>.</em></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve seen misconceptions about Unicode crop up regularly in posts discussing it. One very common
misconception I&rsquo;ve seen is that <em>code points have cross-language intrinsic meaning</em>.</p>

<p>It usually comes up when people are comparing UTF8 and UTF32. Folks start implying that code points
<em>mean</em> something, and that O(1) indexing or slicing at code point boundaries is a useful operation.
I&rsquo;ve also seen this assumption manifest itself in actual programs which make incorrect assumptions
about the nature of code points and mess things up when fed non-Latin text.</p>

<p>If you like reading about unicode, you might also want to go through <a href="https://eev.ee/blog/2015/09/12/dark-corners-of-unicode/">Eevee&rsquo;s article</a>
on the dark corners of unicode. Great read!</p>

<h2>Encodings</h2>

<p>So, anyway, we have some popular encodings for Unicode. UTF8 encodes 7-bit code points as a single
byte, 11-bit code points as two bytes, 16-bit code points as 3 bytes, and 21-bit code points as four
bytes. UTF-16 encodes the first three in two bytes, and the last one as four bytes (logically, a
pair of two-byte code units). UTF-32 encodes all code points as 4-byte code units. UTF-16 is mostly
a &ldquo;worst of both worlds&rdquo; compromise at this point, and the main programming language I can think of
that uses it (and exposes it in this form) is Javascript, and that too in a broken way.</p>

<p>The nice thing about UTF8 is that it saves space. Of course, that is subjective and dependent on
the script you use most commonly, for example my first name is 12 bytes in UTF-8 but only 4
in ISCII (or a hypothetical unicode-based encoding that swapped the Devanagri Unicode block with
the ASCII block). It also uses more space over the very non-hypothetical UTF-16 encoding if you
tend to use code points in the U+0800 - U+FFFF range. It always uses less space than UTF-32 however.</p>

<p>A commonly touted disadvantage of UTF-8 is that string indexing is <code>O(n)</code>. Because code points take
up a variable number of bytes, you won&rsquo;t know where the 5th codepoint is until you scan the string
and look for it. UTF-32 doesn&rsquo;t have this problem; it&rsquo;s always <code>4 * index</code> bytes away.</p>

<p>The problem here is that indexing by code point shouldn&rsquo;t be an operation you ever need!</p>

<h2>Indexing by code point</h2>

<p>The main time you want to be able to index by code point is if you&rsquo;re implementing algorithms
defined in the unicode spec that operate on unicode strings (casefolding, segmentation, NFD/NFC).
Most if not all of these algorithms operate on whole strings, so implementing them
as an iteration pass is usually necessary anyway, so you don&rsquo;t lose anything if you can&rsquo;t
do arbitrary code point indexing.</p>

<p>But for application logic, dealing with code points doesn&rsquo;t really make sense. This is because
code points have no intrinsic meaning. They are not &ldquo;characters&rdquo;. I&rsquo;m using scare quotes here
because a &ldquo;character&rdquo; isn&rsquo;t a well-defined concept either, but we&rsquo;ll get to that later.</p>

<p>For example, &ldquo;e&#x0301;&rdquo; is two code points (<code>e</code> +<code>́</code>), where one of them is a combining accent. My name,
&ldquo;मनीष&rdquo;, visually looks like three &ldquo;characters&rdquo;, but is four code points. The &ldquo;नी&rdquo; is made up of <code>न</code>
+ <code>ी</code>. My last name contains a &ldquo;character&rdquo; made up of three code points (and multiple two-code-point
&ldquo;characters&rdquo;). The flag emoji &ldquo;🇺🇸&rdquo; is also made of two code points, <code>🇺</code> + <code>🇸</code>.</p>

<p>One false assumption that&rsquo;s often made is that code points are a single column wide. They&rsquo;re not.
They sometimes bunch up to form characters that fit in single &ldquo;columns&rdquo;. This is often dependent on
the font, and if your application relies on this, you should be querying the font. There are even
code points like U+FDFD (﷽) which are often rendered multiple columns wide. In fact, in my
<em>monospace</em> font in my text editor, that character is rendered <em>almost</em> 12 columns wide. Yes,
&ldquo;almost&rdquo;, subsequent characters get offset a tiny bit. I don&rsquo;t know why.</p>

<p>Another false assumption is that editing actions (selection, backspace, cut, paste) operate on code
points. In both Chrome and Firefox, selection will often include multiple code points. All the
multi-code-point examples I gave above fall into this category. An interesting testcase for this is
the string &ldquo;ᄀᄀᄀ각ᆨᆨ&rdquo;, which will rarely if ever render as a single &ldquo;character&rdquo; but will be considered
as one for the purposes of selection, pretty much universally. I&rsquo;ll get to why this is later.</p>

<p>Backspace can gobble multiple code points at once too, but the heuristics are different. The reason
behind this is that backspace needs to mirror the act of typing, and while typing sometimes
constructs multi-codepoint characters, backspace decomposes it piece by piece. In cases where a
multi-codepoint &ldquo;character&rdquo; <em>can</em> be logically decomposed (e.g. &ldquo;letter + accent&rdquo;), backspace will
decompose it, by removing the accent or whatever. But some multi-codepoint characters are not
&ldquo;constructions&rdquo; of general concepts that should be exposed to the user. For example, a user should
never need to know that the &ldquo;🇺🇸&rdquo; flag emoji is made of <code>🇺</code> + <code>🇸</code>, and hitting backspace on it should
delete both codepoints. Similarly, variation selectors and other such code points shouldn&rsquo;t
be treated as their own unit when backspacing.</p>

<p>On my Mac most builtin apps (which I presume use the OSX UI toolkits) seem to use the same
heuristics that Firefox/Chrome use for selection for both selection and backspace. While the
treatment of code points in editing contexts is not consistent, it seems like applications
consistently do not consider code points as &ldquo;editing units&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Now, it is true that you often need <em>some</em> way to index a string. For example, if you have a large
document and need to represent a slice of it. This could be a user-selection, or something delimeted
by markup. Basically, you&rsquo;ve already gone through the document and have a section you want to be
able to refer to later without copying it out.</p>

<p>However, you don&rsquo;t need code point indexing here, byte
indexing works fine! UTF8 is designed so that you can check if you&rsquo;re on a code point boundary even
if you just byte-index directly. It does this by restricting the kinds of bytes allowed. One-byte
code points never have the high bit set (ASCII). All other code points have the high bit set in each
byte. The first byte of multibyte codepoints always starts with a sequence that specifies the number
of bytes in the codepoint, and such sequences can&rsquo;t be found in the lower-order bytes of any
multibyte codepoint. You can see this visually in the table <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTF-8#Description">here</a>. The upshot of all this
is that you just need to check the current byte if you want to be sure you&rsquo;re on a codepoint
boundary, and if you receive an arbitrarily byte-sliced string, you will not mistake it for
something else. It&rsquo;s not possible to have a valid code point be a subslice of another, or form a
valid code point by subslicing a sequence of two different ones by cutting each in half.</p>

<p>So all you need to do is keep track of the byte indices, and use them for slicing it later.</p>

<p>All in all, it&rsquo;s important to always remember that &ldquo;code point&rdquo; doesn&rsquo;t have intrinsic meaning. If
you need to do a segmentation operation on a string, find out what <em>exactly</em> you&rsquo;re looking for, and
what concept maps closest to that. It&rsquo;s rare that &ldquo;code point&rdquo; is the concept you&rsquo;re looking for.
In <em>most</em> cases, what you&rsquo;re looking for instead is &ldquo;grapheme cluster&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>Grapheme clusters</h2>

<p>The concept of a &ldquo;character&rdquo; is a nebulous one. Is &ldquo;&#x1100;&#x1161;&#x11A8;&rdquo; a single character, or
three? How about &ldquo;नी&rdquo;? Or &ldquo;நி&rdquo;? Or the &ldquo;👨‍❤️‍👨&rdquo; emoji<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>? Or the &ldquo;👨‍👨‍👧‍👧&rdquo; family emoji<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>?
Different scripts have different concepts which may not clearly map to the Latin notion of &ldquo;letter&rdquo;
or our programmery notion of &ldquo;character&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Unicode itself gives the term <a href="http://unicode.org/glossary/#character">&ldquo;character&rdquo;</a> multiple incompatible meanings, and as
far as I know doesn&rsquo;t use the term in any normative text.</p>

<p>Often, you need to deal with what is actually displayed to the user. A lot of terminal emulators do
this wrong, and end up messing up cursor placement. I used to use irssi-xmpp to keep my Facebook and
Gchat conversations in my IRC client, but I eventually stopped as I was increasingly chatting in
Marathi or Hindi and I prefer using the actual script over romanizing<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, and it would just break
my terminal<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>. Also, they got rid of the XMPP bridge but I&rsquo;d already cut down on it by then.</p>

<p>So sometimes, you need an API querying what the font is doing. Generally, when talking about the
actual rendered image, the term &ldquo;glyph&rdquo; or &ldquo;glyph image&rdquo; is used.</p>

<p>However, you can&rsquo;t always query the font. Text itself exists independent of rendering, and sometimes
you need a rendering-agnostic way of segmenting it into &ldquo;characters&rdquo;.</p>

<p>For this, Unicode has a concept of <a href="http://unicode.org/glossary/#grapheme_cluster">&ldquo;grapheme cluster&rdquo;</a>. There&rsquo;s also &ldquo;extended grapheme
cluster&rdquo; (EGC), which is basically an updated version of the concept. In this post, whenever
I use the term &ldquo;grapheme cluster&rdquo;, I am talking about EGCs.</p>

<p>The term is defined and explored in <a href="http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr29/#Grapheme_Cluster_Boundaries">UAX #29</a>. It starts by pinning down the still-nebulous
concept of &ldquo;user-perceived character&rdquo; (&ldquo;a basic unit of a writing system for a language&rdquo;),
and then declares the concept of a &ldquo;grapheme cluster&rdquo; to be an approximation to this notion
that we can determine programmatically.</p>

<p>A rough definition of grapheme cluster is a &ldquo;horizontally segmentable unit of text&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The spec goes into detail as to the exact algorithm that segments text at grapheme cluster
boundaries. All of the examples I gave in the first paragraph of this section are single grapheme
clusters. So is &ldquo;ᄀᄀᄀ각ᆨᆨ&rdquo; (or &ldquo;ᄀᄀᄀ&#x1100;&#x1161;&#x11A8;ᆨᆨ&rdquo;), which apparently is considered a
single syllable block in Hangul even though it is not of the typical form of leading consonant +
vowel + optional tail consonant, but is not something you&rsquo;d see in modern Korean. The spec
explicitly talks of this case so it seems to be on purpose. I like this string because nothing I
know of renders it as a single glyph; so you can easily use it to tell if a particular segmentation-
aware operation uses grapheme clusters as segmentation. If you try and select it, in most browsers
you will be forced to select the whole thing, but backspace will delete the jamos one by one. For
the second string, backspace will decompose the core syllable block too (in the first string the
syllable block &#x1100;&#x1161;&#x11A8; is &ldquo;precomposed&rdquo; as a single code point, in the second one I
built it using combining jamos).</p>

<p>Basically, unless you have very specific requirements or are able to query the font, use an API that
segments strings into grapheme clusters wherever you need to deal with the notion of &ldquo;character&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>Language defaults</h2>

<p>Now, a lot of languages by default are now using Unicode-aware encodings. This is great. It gets rid
of the misconception that characters are one byte long.</p>

<p>But it doesn&rsquo;t get rid of the misconception that user-perceived characters are one code point long.</p>

<p>There are only two languages I know of which handle this well: Swift and Perl 6. I don&rsquo;t know much
about Perl 6&rsquo;s thing so I can&rsquo;t really comment on it, but I am really happy with what Swift does:</p>

<p>In Swift, the <code>Character</code> type is an extended grapheme cluster. This does mean that a
character itself is basically a string, since EGCs can be arbitrarily many code points long.</p>

<p>All the APIs by default deal with EGCs. The length of a string is the number of EGCs in it. They
are indexed by EGC. Iteration yields EGCs. The default comparison algorithm uses unicode
canonical equivalence, which I think is kind of neat. Of course, APIs that work with code
points are exposed too, you can iterate over the code points using <code>.unicodeScalars</code>.</p>

<p>The internal encoding itself is &hellip; weird (and as far as I can tell not publicly exposed), but as a
higher level language I think it&rsquo;s fine to do things like that.</p>

<p>I strongly feel that languages should be moving in this direction, having defaults involving
grapheme clusters.</p>

<p>Rust, for example, gets a lot of things right &ndash; it has UTF-8 strings. It internally uses byte
indices in slices. Explicit slicing usually uses byte indices too, and will panic if out of bounds.
The non-O(1) methods are all explicit, since you will use an iterator to perform the operation (E.g.
<code>.chars().nth(5)</code>). This encourages people to <em>think</em> about the cost, and it also  encourages people
to coalesce the cost with nearby iterations &ndash; if you are going to do multiple <code>O(n)</code> things, do
them in a single iteration! Rust <code>char</code>s represent code points. <code>.char_indices()</code> is
a useful string iteration method that bridges the gap between byte indexing and code points.</p>

<p>However, while the documentation does mention grapheme clusters, the stdlib is not aware of the
concept of grapheme clusters at all. The default &ldquo;fundamental&rdquo; unit of the string in Rust is
a code point, and the operations revolve around that. If you want grapheme clusters, you
may use <a href="https://unicode-rs.github.io/unicode-segmentation/unicode_segmentation/trait.UnicodeSegmentation.html#tymethod.graphemes"><code>unicode-segmentation</code></a></p>

<p>Now, Rust is a systems programming language and it just wouldn&rsquo;t do to have expensive grapheme
segmentation operations all over your string defaults. I&rsquo;m very happy that the expensive <code>O(n)</code>
operations are all only possible with explicit acknowledgement of the cost. So I do think that going
the Swift route would be counterproductive for Rust. Not that it <em>can</em> anyway, due to backwards
compatibility :)</p>

<p>But I would prefer if the grapheme segmentation methods were in the stdlib (they used to be).
This is probably not something that will happen, though I should probably push for the unicode
crates being move into the nursery at least.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Emoji may not render as a single glyph depending on the font.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>While writing this paragraph I discovered that wrapping text that contains lots of family emoji hangs Sublime. Neat.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>It&rsquo;s possible to make work. You need a good terminal emulator, with the right settings, the right settings in your env vars, the right settings in irssi, and the right settings in screen. I think my current setup works well with non-ascii text but I&rsquo;m not sure what I did to make it happen.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Part of the reason here is that I just find romanization confusing. There are some standardized ways to romanize which don&rsquo;t get used much. My friends and I romanize one way, different from the standardizations. My family members romanize things a completely different way and it&rsquo;s a bit hard to read. Then again, romanization <em>does</em> hide the fact that my spelling in Hindi is atrocious :)<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rust Tidbits: What Is a Lang Item?]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2017/01/11/rust-tidbits-what-is-a-lang-item/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-11T21:01:13-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2017/01/11/rust-tidbits-what-is-a-lang-item</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Rust is not a simple language. As with any such language, it has many little tidbits of complexity
that most folks aren&rsquo;t aware of. Many of these tidbits are ones which may not practically matter
much for everyday Rust programming, but are interesting to know. Others may be more useful. I&rsquo;ve
found that a lot of these aren&rsquo;t documented anywhere (not that they always should be), and sometimes
depend on knowledge of compiler internals or history. As a fan of programming trivia myself, I&rsquo;ve
decided to try writing about these things whenever I come across them. &ldquo;Tribal Knowledge&rdquo; shouldn&rsquo;t
be a thing in a programming community; and trivia is fun!</em></p>

<p>Previously in tidbits: <a href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2017/01/10/rust-tidbits-box-is-special/"><code>Box</code> is Special</a></p>

<p>Last time I talked about <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> and how it is a special snowflake. Corey <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/rust/comments/5nb86x/rust_tidbits_box_is_special/dca4y6n/?utm_content=permalink&amp;utm_medium=front&amp;utm_source=reddit&amp;utm_name=rust">asked</a> that
I write more about lang items, which are basically all of the special snowflakes in the stdlib.</p>

<p>So what <em>is</em> a lang item? Lang items are a way for the stdlib (and libcore) to define types, traits,
functions, and other items which the compiler needs to know about.</p>

<p>For example, when you write <code>x + y</code>, the compiler will effectively desugar that into
<code>Add::add(x, y)</code><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. How did it know what trait to call? Did it just insert a call to
<code>::core::Add::add</code> and hope the trait was defined there? This is what C++ does;
the Itanium ABI spec expects functions of certain names
to just <em>exist</em>, which the compiler is supposed to call in various cases. The
<code>__cxa_guard_*</code> functions from C++s deferred-initialization local statics (which
I&rsquo;ve <a href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2015/06/26/adventures-in-systems-programming-c-plus-plus-local-statics/">explored in the past</a>) are an example of this. You&rsquo;ll find that the spec is
full of similar <code>__cxa</code> functions. While the spec just expects certain types,
e.g. <code>std::type_traits</code> (&ldquo;Type properties&rdquo; § 20.10.4.3), to be magic and exist in certain locations,
the compilers seem to implement them using intrinsics like <code>__is_trivial&lt;T&gt;</code> which aren&rsquo;t defined
in C++ code at all. So C++ compilers have a mix of solutions here, they partly insert calls
to known ABI functions, and they partly implement &ldquo;special&rdquo; types via intrinsics which
are detected and magicked when the compiler comes across them.</p>

<p>However, this is not Rust&rsquo;s solution. It does not care what the <code>Add</code> trait is named or where it is
placed. Instead, it knew where the trait for addition was located because <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/2782e8f8fcefdce77c5e0dd0846c15c4c5103d84/src/libcore/ops.rs#L243"><em>we told it</em></a>.
When you put <code>#[lang = "add"]</code> on a trait, the compiler knows to call <code>YourTrait::add(x, y)</code> when it
encounters the addition operator. Of course, usually the compiler will already have been told about
such a trait since libcore is usually the first library in the pipeline. If you want to actually use
this, you need to <em>replace libcore</em>.</p>

<p>Huh? You can&rsquo;t do that, can you?</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not a big secret that you can compile rust without the stdlib using
<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/no-stdlib.html"><code>#![no_std]</code></a>. This is useful in cases when you are on an embedded system and can&rsquo;t
rely on an allocator existing. It&rsquo;s also useful for writing your own alternate stdlib, though
that&rsquo;s not something folks do often. Of course, libstd itself <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/2782e8f8fcefdce77c5e0dd0846c15c4c5103d84/src/libstd/lib.rs#L213-L214">uses <code>#![no_std]</code></a>,
because without it the compiler will happily inject an <code>extern crate std</code> while trying to compile
libstd and the universe will implode.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s less known is that you can do the same thing with libcore, via <code>#![no_core]</code>. And, of course,
libcore <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/2782e8f8fcefdce77c5e0dd0846c15c4c5103d84/src/libcore/lib.rs#L65">uses it</a> to avoid the cyclic dependency. Unlike <code>#![no_std]</code>, <code>no_core</code> is
a nightly-only feature that we may never stabilize<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. <code>#![no_core]</code> is something that&rsquo;s basically
only to be used if you <em>are</em> libcore (or you are an alternate Rust stdlib/core implementation
trying to emulate it).</p>

<p>Still, it&rsquo;s possible to write a working Rust binary in <code>no_core</code> mode:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">#![feature(no_core)]
#![feature(lang_items)]

// Look at me.
// Look at me.
// I'm the libcore now.
#![no_core]

// Tell the compiler to link to appropriate runtime libs
// (This way I don't have to specify `-l` flags explicitly)
#[cfg(target_os = "linux")]
#[link(name = "c")]
extern {}
#[cfg(target_os = "macos")]
#[link(name = "System")]
extern {}

// Compiler needs these to proceed
#[lang = "sized"]
pub trait Sized {}
#[lang = "copy"]
pub trait Copy {}

// `main` isn't the actual entry point, `start` is.
#[lang = "start"]
fn start(_main: *const u8, _argc: isize, _argv: *const *const u8) -&gt; isize {
    // we can't really do much in this benighted hellhole of
    // an environment without bringing in more libraries.
    // We can make syscalls, segfault, and set the exit code.
    // To be sure that this actually ran, let's set the exit code.
    42
}

// still need a main unless we want to use `#![no_main]`
// won't actually get called; `start()` is supposed to call it
fn main() {}
</code></pre>

<p>If you run this, the program will exit with exit code 42.</p>

<p>Note that this already adds two lang items. <code>Sized</code> and <code>Copy</code>. It&rsquo;s usually worth
<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/2782e8f8fcefdce77c5e0dd0846c15c4c5103d84/src/libcore/marker.rs#L88-L94">looking at the lang item in libcore</a> and copying it over unless you want to make
tweaks. Beware that tweaks may not always work; not only does the compiler expect the lang item
to exist, it expects it to make sense. There are properties of the lang item that it assumes
are true, and it may cause assertions in the code. In this case I do have a tweak, since
the original definition of <code>Copy</code> is <code>pub trait Copy: Clone {}</code>, but I know that this tweak
will work.</p>

<p>Lang items are usually only required when you do an operation which needs them. There are 72 non-
deprecated lang items and we only had to define three of them here. &ldquo;start&rdquo; is necessary to, well,
start executables, and <code>Copy</code>/<code>Sized</code> are very crucial to how the compiler reasons about types and
must exist.</p>

<p>But let&rsquo;s try doing something that will trigger a lang item to be required:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">pub static X: u8 = 1;
</code></pre>

<p>Rust will immediately complain:</p>

<pre><code>$ rustc test.rs
error: requires `sync` lang_item
</code></pre>

<p>This is because Rust wants to enforce that types in statics (which can be accessed concurrently)
are safe when accessed concurrently, i.e., they implement <code>Sync</code>. We haven&rsquo;t defined <code>Sync</code> yet,
so Rust doesn&rsquo;t know how to enforce this restruction. The <code>Sync</code> trait is defined with the &ldquo;sync&rdquo;
lang item, so we need to do:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">pub static X: u8 = 1;

#[lang = "sync"]
pub unsafe trait Sync {}
unsafe impl Sync for u8 {}
</code></pre>

<p>Note that the trait doesn&rsquo;t have to be called <code>Sync</code> here, any trait name would work. This
definition is also a slight <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/2782e8f8fcefdce77c5e0dd0846c15c4c5103d84/src/libcore/marker.rs#L343-L351">departure from the one in the stdlib</a>, and in general you
should include the auto trait impl (instead of specifically using <code>unsafe impl Sync for u8 {}</code>)
since the compiler may assume it exists. Our code is small enough for this to not matter.</p>

<p>Alright, let&rsquo;s try defining our own addition trait as before. First, let&rsquo;s see
what happens if we try to add a struct when addition isn&rsquo;t defined:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">struct Foo;
#[lang = "start"]
fn start(_main: *const u8, _argc: isize, _argv: *const *const u8) -&gt; isize {
    Foo + Foo
}
</code></pre>

<p>We get an error:</p>

<pre><code>$ rustc test.rs
error[E0369]: binary operation `+` cannot be applied to type `Foo`
  --&gt; test.rs:33:5
   |
33 |     Foo + Foo
   |     ^^^
   |
note: an implementation of `std::ops::Add` might be missing for `Foo`
  --&gt; test.rs:33:5
   |
33 |     Foo + Foo
   |     ^^^

error: aborting due to previous error
</code></pre>

<p>It is interesting to note that here the compiler <em>did</em> refer to <code>Add</code> by its path.
This is because the diagnostics in the compiler are free to assume that libcore
exists. However, the actual error just noted that it doesn&rsquo;t know how to add two
<code>Foo</code>s. But we can tell it how!</p>

<pre><code class="rust">#[lang = "add"]
trait MyAdd&lt;RHS&gt; {
    type Output;
    fn add(self, other: RHS) -&gt; Self::Output;
}

impl MyAdd&lt;Foo&gt; for Foo {
    type Output = isize;
    fn add(self, other: Foo) -&gt; isize {
        return 42;
    }
}

struct Foo;
#[lang = "start"]
fn start(_main: *const u8, _argc: isize, _argv: *const *const u8) -&gt; isize {
    Foo + Foo
}
</code></pre>

<p>This will compile fine and the exit code of the program will be 42.</p>

<p>An interesting bit of behavior is what happens if we try to add two numbers. It will give us the
same kind of error, even though I mentioned before that the addition of concrete primitives doesn&rsquo;t
go through <code>Add::add</code>. However, any addition operation still checks if <code>Add::add</code> is implemented,
even though it won&rsquo;t get <em>used</em> in the case of a primitive. We can even verify this!</p>

<pre><code class="rust">#[lang = "add"]
trait MyAdd&lt;RHS&gt; {
    type Output;
    fn add(self, other: RHS) -&gt; Self::Output;
}

impl MyAdd&lt;isize&gt; for isize {
    type Output = isize;
    fn add(self, other: isize) -&gt; isize {
        self + other + 50
    }
}

struct Foo;
#[lang = "start"]
fn start(_main: *const u8, _argc: isize, _argv: *const *const u8) -&gt; isize {
    40 + 2
}
</code></pre>

<p>This will need to be compiled with <code>-C opt-level=2</code>, since numeric addition in debug mode panics on
wrap and we haven&rsquo;t defined the <code>"panic"</code> lang item to teach the compiler <em>how</em> to panic.</p>

<p>It will exit with 42, not 92, since while the <code>Add</code> implementation is required for this to type
check, it doesn&rsquo;t actually get used.</p>

<hr />

<p>So what lang items <em>are</em> there, and why are they lang items? There&rsquo;s a <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L252-L363">big list</a> in the
compiler. Let&rsquo;s go through them:</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L254-L272"><code>ImplItem</code> ones</a> (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/2782e8f8fcefdce77c5e0dd0846c15c4c5103d84/src/libstd_unicode/char.rs#L134-L135">core</a>) are used to mark implementations on
primitive types. <code>char</code> has some methods, and <em>someone</em> has to say <code>impl char</code> to define them. But
coherence only allows us to impl methods on types defined in our own crate, and <code>char</code> isn&rsquo;t defined
&hellip; in any crate, so how do we add methods to it? <code>#[lang = "char"]</code> provides an escape hatch;
applying that to <code>impl char</code> will allow you to break the coherence rules and add methods,
<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/2782e8f8fcefdce77c5e0dd0846c15c4c5103d84/src/libstd_unicode/char.rs#L134-L135">as is done in the standard library</a>. Since lang items can only be defined once, only
a single crate gets the honor of adding methods to <code>char</code>, so we don&rsquo;t have any of the issues that
arise from sidestepping coherence.</p>

<p>There are a bunch for the <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L274-L278">marker traits</a> (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/408c2f7827be838aadcd05bd041dab94388af35d/src/libcore/marker.rs#L41-L356">core</a>):</p>

<ul>
<li><code>Send</code> is a lang item because you are allowed to use it in a <code>+</code> bound in a trait object (<code>Box&lt;SomeTrait+Send+Sync&gt;</code>), and the compiler caches it aggressively</li>
<li><code>Sync</code> is a lang item for the same reasons as <code>Send</code>, but also because the compiler needs to enforce its implementation on types used in statics</li>
<li><code>Copy</code> is fundamental to classifying values and reasoning about moves/etc, so it needs to be a lang item</li>
<li><code>Sized</code> is also fundamental to reasoning about which values may exist on the stack. It is also magically included as a bound on generic parameters unless excluded with <code>?Sized</code></li>
<li>[<code>Unsize</code>] is implemented automatically on types using a specific set of rules (<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/nomicon/coercions.html">listed in the nomicon</a>). Unlike <code>Send</code> and <code>Sync</code>, this mechanism for autoimplementation is tailored for the use case of <code>Unsize</code> and can&rsquo;t be reused on user-defined marker traits.</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L280"><code>Drop</code> is a lang item</a> (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/408c2f7827be838aadcd05bd041dab94388af35d/src/libcore/ops.rs#L174-L197">core</a>) because the compiler needs to know which types have destructors, and how to call
these destructors.</p>

<p><a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/nightly/std/ops/trait.CoerceUnsized.html"><code>CoerceUnsized</code></a> <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L282">is a lang item</a>
(<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/408c2f7827be838aadcd05bd041dab94388af35d/src/libcore/ops.rs#L2743-L2746">core</a>) because the compiler is allowed to perform
<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rfcs/blob/master/text/0982-dst-coercion.md">DST coercions</a> (<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/nomicon/coercions.html">nomicon</a>) when it is implemented.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L284-L307">All of the builtin operators</a> (also <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L311-L312"><code>Deref</code></a>
and <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L318-L319"><code>PartialEq</code>/<code>PartialOrd</code></a>, which are listed later in the file) (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/408c2f7827be838aadcd05bd041dab94388af35d/src/libcore/ops.rs#L243-L2035">core</a>)
are lang items because the compiler needs to know what trait to require (and call)
when it comes across such an operation.</p>

<p><a href="http://doc.rust-lang.org/std/cell/struct.UnsafeCell.html"><code>UnsafeCell</code></a> <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L309">is a lang item</a>
(<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/408c2f7827be838aadcd05bd041dab94388af35d/src/libcore/cell.rs#L1065-L1069">core</a>) because it has very special semantics; it prevents
certain optimizations. Specifically, Rust is allowed to reorder reads/writes to <code>&amp;mut foo</code> with the
assumption that the local variable holding the reference is the only alias allowed to read from
or write to the data, and it is allowed to reorder reads from <code>&amp;foo</code> assuming that no other alias
writes to it. We tell LLVM that these types are <code>noalias</code>. <code>UnsafeCell&lt;T&gt;</code> turns this optimization
off, allowing writes to <code>&amp;UnsafeCell&lt;T&gt;</code> references. This is used in the implementation of interior
mutability types like <code>Cell&lt;T&gt;</code>, <code>RefCell&lt;T&gt;</code>, and <code>Mutex&lt;T&gt;</code>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L314-L316"><code>Fn</code> traits</a> (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/408c2f7827be838aadcd05bd041dab94388af35d/src/libcore/ops.rs#L2556-L2659">core</a>) are used in dispatching function calls,
and can be specified with special syntax sugar, so they need to be lang items. They also
get autoimplemented on closures.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L321">The &ldquo;str_eq&rdquo; lang item</a> is outdated. It <em>used</em> to specify how to check the equality
of a string value against a literal string pattern in a <code>match</code> (<code>match</code> uses structural equality,
not <code>PartialEq::eq</code>), however I believe this behavior is now hardcoded in the compiler.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L332-L334">The panic-related lang items</a> (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/408c2f7827be838aadcd05bd041dab94388af35d/src/libcore/panicking.rs#L39-L58">core</a>) exist because rustc itself
inserts panics in a few places. The first one, <code>"panic"</code>, is used for integer overflow panics in debug mode, and
<code>"panic_bounds_check"</code> is used for out of bounds indexing panics on slices. The last one,
<code>"panic_fmt"</code> hooks into a function defined later in libstd.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L336-L337"><code>"exchange_malloc"</code> and <code>"box_free"</code></a> (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/408c2f7827be838aadcd05bd041dab94388af35d/src/liballoc/heap.rs#L129-L152">alloc</a>) are for
telling the compiler which functions to call in case it needs to do a <code>malloc()</code> or <code>free()</code>. These
are used when constructing <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> via placement <code>box</code> syntax and when moving out of a deref of a
box.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L338"><code>"strdup_uniq"</code></a> seemed to be used in the past for moving string literals to the heap,
but is no longer used.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve already seen <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L340">the start lang item</a> (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/libstd/rt.rs#L31-L67">std</a>) being used in our
minimal example program. This function is basically where you find Rust&rsquo;s &ldquo;runtime&rdquo;: it gets called
with a pointer to main and the command line arguments, it sets up the &ldquo;runtime&rdquo;, calls main, and
tears down anything it needs to. Rust has a C-like minimal runtime, so
<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/libstd/rt.rs#L31-L67">the actual libstd definition</a> doesn&rsquo;t do much.
But you theoretically could stick a very heavy runtime initialization routine here.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L342-L344">exception handling lang items</a> (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/408c2f7827be838aadcd05bd041dab94388af35d/src/libpanic_unwind/seh.rs">panic_unwind</a>, in multiple
platform-specific modules) specify various bits of the exception handling behavior. These hooks are
called during various steps of unwinding: <code>eh_personality</code> is called when determining whether
or not to stop at a stack frame or unwind up to the next one. <code>eh_unwind_resume</code> is the routine
called when the unwinding code wishes to resume unwinding after calling destructors in a landing
pad. <code>msvc_try_filter</code> defines some parameter that MSVC needs in its unwinding code. I don&rsquo;t
understand it, and apparently, <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/408c2f7827be838aadcd05bd041dab94388af35d/src/libpanic_unwind/seh.rs#L232">neither does the person who wrote it</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L346"><code>"owned_box"</code></a> (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/408c2f7827be838aadcd05bd041dab94388af35d/src/liballoc/boxed.rs#L105-L107">alloc</a>) lang item tells the compiler which type is
the <code>Box</code> type. In my previous post I covered how <code>Box</code> is special; this lang item is how the
compiler finds impls on <code>Box</code> and knows what the type is. Unlike the other primitives, <code>Box</code> doesn&rsquo;t
actually have a type name (like <code>bool</code>) that can be used if you&rsquo;re writing libcore or libstd. This
lang item gives <code>Box</code> a type name that can be used to refer to it. (It also defines some,
but not all, of the semantics of <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code>)</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L348"><code>"phantom_data"</code></a> (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/2782e8f8fcefdce77c5e0dd0846c15c4c5103d84/src/libcore/marker.rs#L544-L546">core</a>) type itself is allowed to have
an unused type parameter, and it can be used to help fix the variance and drop behavior
of a generic type. More on this in <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/nomicon/phantom-data.html">the nomicon</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1ca100d0428985f916eea153886762bed3909771/src/librustc/middle/lang_items.rs#L360"><code>"non_zero"</code></a> lang item (<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/2782e8f8fcefdce77c5e0dd0846c15c4c5103d84/src/libcore/nonzero.rs#L38-L42">core</a>) marks the <code>NonZero&lt;T&gt;</code> type,
a type which is guaranteed to never contain a bit pattern of only zeroes. This is used inside things
like <code>Rc&lt;T&gt;</code> and <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> &ndash; we know that the pointers in these can/should never be null, so they
contain a <code>NonZero&lt;*const T&gt;</code>. When used inside an enum like <code>Option&lt;Rc&lt;T&gt;&gt;</code>, the discriminant
(the &ldquo;tag&rdquo; value that distinguishes between <code>Some</code> and <code>None</code>) is no longer necessary, since
we can mark the <code>None</code> case as the case where the bits occupied by <code>NonZero</code> in the <code>Some</code> case
are zero. Beware, this optimization also applies to C-like enums that don&rsquo;t have a variant
corresponding to a discriminant value of zero (unless they are <code>#[repr(C)]</code>)</p>

<p>There are also a bunch of deprecated lang items there. For example, <code>NoCopy</code> used to be a struct
that could be dropped within a type to make it not implement <code>Copy</code>; in the past <code>Copy</code>
implementations were automatic like <code>Send</code> and <code>Sync</code> are today. <code>NoCopy</code> was the way to opt out.
There also used to be <code>NoSend</code> and <code>NoSync</code>. <code>CovariantType</code>/<code>CovariantLifetime</code>/etc were the
predecessors of <code>PhantomData</code>; they could be used to specify variance relations of a type with its
type or lifetime parameters, but you can now do this with providing the right <code>PhantomData</code>, e.g.
<code>InvariantType&lt;T&gt;</code> is now <code>PhantomData&lt;Cell&lt;T&gt;&gt;</code>.
The <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/nomicon/subtyping.html">nomicon</a> has more on variance. I don&rsquo;t know why these lang items haven&rsquo;t been
removed (they don&rsquo;t work anymore anyway); the only consumer of them is libcore so &ldquo;deprecating&rdquo; them
seems unnecessary. It&rsquo;s probably an oversight.</p>

<p>Interestingly, <code>Iterator</code> and <code>IntoIterator</code> are <em>not</em> lang items, even though they are used in <code>for</code>
loops. Instead, the compiler inserts hardcoded calls to <code>::std::iter::IntoIterator::into_iter</code> and
<code>::std::iter::Iterator::next</code>, and a hardcoded reference to <code>::std::option::Option</code> (The paths use
<code>core</code> in <code>no_std</code> mode). This is probably because the compiler desugars <code>for</code> loops before type
resolution is done, so withut this, libcore would not be able to use for loops since the compiler
wouldn&rsquo;t know what calls to insert in place of the loops while compiling.</p>

<hr />

<p>Basically, whenever the compiler needs to use special treatment with an item &ndash; whether it be
dispatching calls to functions and trait methods in various situations, conferring special semantics
to types/traits, or requiring traits to be implemented, the type will be defined in the standard
library (libstd, libcore, or one of the crates behind the libstd façade), and marked as a lang item.</p>

<p>Some of the lang items are useful/necessary when working without libstd. Most only come into play if
you want to replace libcore, which is a pretty niche thing to do, and knowing about them is rarely
useful outside of the realm of compiler hacking.</p>

<p>But, like with the <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> madness, I still find this quite interesting, even if it isn&rsquo;t generally
useful!</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Though as we learned in the previous post, when <code>x</code> and <code>y</code> are known numeric types it will bypass the trait and directly generate an add instruction in LLVM<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>To be clear, I&rsquo;m not aware of any plans to eventually stabilize this. It&rsquo;s something that could happen.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rust Tidbits: Box Is Special]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2017/01/10/rust-tidbits-box-is-special/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-10T22:59:43-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2017/01/10/rust-tidbits-box-is-special</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rust is not a simple language. As with any such language, it has many little tidbits of complexity
that most folks aren&rsquo;t aware of. Many of these tidbits are ones which may not practically matter
much for everyday Rust programming, but are interesting to know. Others may be more useful. I&rsquo;ve
found that a lot of these aren&rsquo;t documented anywhere (not that they always should be), and sometimes
depend on knowledge of compiler internals or history. As a fan of programming trivia myself, I&rsquo;ve
decided to try writing about these things whenever I come across them. &ldquo;Tribal Knowledge&rdquo; shouldn&rsquo;t
be a thing in a programming community; and trivia is fun!</p>

<hr />

<p>So. <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code>. Your favorite heap allocation type that nobody uses<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>I was discussing some stuff on the rfcs repo when
<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rfcs/issues/1850#issuecomment-271766300">@burdges realized that <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> has a funky <code>Deref</code> impl</a>.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/e4fee525e04838dabc82beed5ae1a06051be53fd/src/liballoc/boxed.rs#L502">look at it</a>:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">#[stable(feature = "rust1", since = "1.0.0")]
impl&lt;T: ?Sized&gt; Deref for Box&lt;T&gt; {
    type Target = T;

    fn deref(&amp;self) -&gt; &amp;T {
        &amp;**self
    }
}

#[stable(feature = "rust1", since = "1.0.0")]
impl&lt;T: ?Sized&gt; DerefMut for Box&lt;T&gt; {
    fn deref_mut(&amp;mut self) -&gt; &amp;mut T {
        &amp;mut **self
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Wait, what? <em>Squints</em></p>

<pre><code class="rust">    fn deref(&amp;self) -&gt; &amp;T {
        &amp;**self
    }
</code></pre>

<p><em>The call is coming from inside the house!</em></p>

<p>In case you didn&rsquo;t realize it, this deref impl returns <code>&amp;**self</code> &ndash; since <code>self</code>
is an <code>&amp;Box&lt;T&gt;</code>, dereferencing it once will provide a <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code>, and the second dereference
will dereference the box to provide a <code>T</code>. We then wrap it in a reference and return it.</p>

<p>But wait, we are <em>defining</em> how a <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> is to be dereferenced (that&rsquo;s what <code>Deref::deref</code> is
for!), such a definition cannot itself dereference a <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code>! That&rsquo;s infinite recursion.</p>

<p>And indeed. For any other type such a <code>deref</code> impl would recurse infinitely. If you run
<a href="https://play.rust-lang.org/?gist=9c8a02336c6816e57c83de39c103ca06&amp;version=stable&amp;backtrace=0">this code</a>:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">use std::ops::Deref;

struct LolBox&lt;T&gt;(T);

impl&lt;T&gt; Deref for LolBox&lt;T&gt; {
    type Target = T;
    fn deref(&amp;self) -&gt; &amp;T {
        &amp;**self
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>the compiler will warn you:</p>

<pre><code class="text">warning: function cannot return without recurring, #[warn(unconditional_recursion)] on by default
 --&gt; &lt;anon&gt;:7:5
  |
7 |     fn deref(&amp;self) -&gt; &amp;T {
  |     ^
  |
note: recursive call site
 --&gt; &lt;anon&gt;:8:10
  |
8 |         &amp;**self
  |          ^^^^^^
  = help: a `loop` may express intention better if this is on purpose
</code></pre>

<p>Actually trying to dereference the type will lead to a stack overflow.</p>

<p>Clearly something is fishy here. This deref impl is similar to <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/52c03d1d619fd25c961bc9de59bcc942b660d5db/src/libcore/ops.rs#L2460">the deref impl for <code>&amp;T</code></a>,
or the <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/52c03d1d619fd25c961bc9de59bcc942b660d5db/src/libcore/ops.rs#L263"><code>Add</code> impl for number types</a>, or any other of the implementations of operators on
primitive types. For example we literally
<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/52c03d1d619fd25c961bc9de59bcc942b660d5db/src/libcore/ops.rs#L263">define <code>Add</code> on two integers to be their addition</a>. The reason these impls need to exist
is so that people can still call <code>Add::add</code> if they need to in generic code and be able to pass
integers to things with an <code>Add</code> bound. But the compiler knows how to use builtin operators on
numbers and dereference borrowed references without these impls. But those are primitive types
which are defined in the compiler, while <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> is just a regular smart pointer struct, right?</p>

<p>Turns out, <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> is special. It, too, is somewhat of a primitive type.</p>

<p>This is partly due to historical accident.</p>

<p>To understand this, we must look back to Ye Olde days of pre-1.0 Rust (ca 2014). Back in these days,
we had none of this newfangled &ldquo;stability&rdquo; business. The compiler broke your code every two weeks.
Of course, you wouldn&rsquo;t <em>know</em> that because the compiler would usually crash before it could tell
you that your code was broken! Sigils roamed the lands freely, and cargo was but a newborn child
which was destined to eventually end the tyranny of Makefiles. People were largely happy knowing
that their closures were safely boxed and their threads sufficiently green.</p>

<p>Back in these days, we didn&rsquo;t have <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code>, <code>Vec&lt;T&gt;</code>, or <code>String</code>. We had <code>~T</code>, <code>~[T]</code>, and <code>~str</code>.
The second two are <em>not</em> equivalent to <code>Box&lt;[T]&gt;</code> and <code>Box&lt;str&gt;</code>, even though they may look like it,
they are both growable containers like <code>Vec&lt;T&gt;</code> and <code>String</code>. <code>~</code> conceptually meant &ldquo;owned&rdquo;, though
IMO that caused more confusion than it was worth.</p>

<p>You created a box using the <code>~</code> operator, e.g. <code>let x = ~1;</code>. It could be dereferenced with the <code>*</code>
operator, and autoderef worked much like it does today.</p>

<p>As a &ldquo;primitive&rdquo; type; like all primitive types, <code>~T</code> was special. The compiler knew things about
it. The compiler knew how to dereference it without an explicit <code>Deref</code> impl. In fact, the <code>Deref</code>
traits <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/pull/12491">came into existence</a> much after <code>~T</code> did. <code>~T</code> never got an explicit <code>Deref</code> impl,
though it probably should have.</p>

<p>Eventually, there was a move to remove sigils from the language. The box constructor <code>~foo</code> was
superseded by <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/pull/11055/">placement <code>box</code> syntax</a>, which still exists in Rust nightly<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Then, the
<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/pull/13904"><code>~T</code> type became <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code></a>. (<code>~[T]</code> and <code>~str</code> would also be removed, though <code>~str</code> took
a very confusing detour with <code>StrBuf</code> first).</p>

<p>However, <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> was still special. It no longer needed special syntax to be referred to or
constructed, but it was still internally a special type. It didn&rsquo;t even have a <code>Deref</code> impl yet,
that came <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/pull/20052">six months later</a>, and it was implemented as <code>&amp;**self</code>, exactly the same
as it is today.</p>

<p>But why does it <em>have</em> to be special now? Rust had all the features it needed (allocations,
ownership, overloadable deref) to implement <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> in pure rust in the stdlib as if it
were a regular type.</p>

<p>Turns out that Rust didn&rsquo;t. You see, because <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> and before it <code>~T</code> were special, their
dereference semantics were implemented in a different part of the code. And, these semantics were
not the same as the ones for <code>DerefImm</code> and <code>DerefMut</code>, which were created for use with other smart
pointers. I don&rsquo;t know if the possibility of being used for <code>~T</code> was considered when
<code>DerefImm</code>/<code>DerefMut</code> were being implemented, or if it was a simple oversight, but <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> has
three pieces of behavior that could not be replicated in pure Rust at the time:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>box foo</code> in a pattern would destructure a box into its contents. It&rsquo;s somewhat the opposite of <code>ref</code></li>
<li><code>box foo()</code> performed placement box, so the result of <code>foo()</code> could be directly written to a preallocated box, reducing extraneous copies</li>
<li>You could <em>move out of deref</em> with <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code></li>
</ul>


<p>The third one is the one that really gets to us here<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.
For a <em>regular</em> type, <code>*foo</code> will produce a temporary that must be immediately borrowed or copied.
You cannot do <code>let x = *y</code> for a non-<code>Copy</code> type. This dereference operation will call
<code>DerefMut::deref_mut</code> or <code>Deref::deref</code> based on how it gets borrowed. With <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code>, you can do
this:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">let x = Box::new(vec![1,2,3,4]);
let y = *x; // moves the vec out into `y`, then deallocates the box
            // but does not call a destructor on the vec
</code></pre>

<p>For any other type, such an operation will produce a &ldquo;cannot move out of a borrow&rdquo; error.</p>

<p>This operation is colloquially called <code>DerefMove</code>, and there has been <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rfcs/pull/178/files?short_path=6f69a99#diff-6f69a990502a98c2eeb172d87269005d">an rfc</a> in the
past for making it into a trait. I suspect that the <code>DerefMove</code> semantics could even have been
removed from <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> before 1.0 (I don&rsquo;t find it <em>necessary</em>), but people had better things to do,
like fixing the million other rough edges of the language that can&rsquo;t be touched after backwards
compatibility is a thing.</p>

<p>So now we&rsquo;re stuck with it. The current status is that <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> is <em>still</em> a special type in the
compiler. By &ldquo;special type&rdquo; I don&rsquo;t just mean that the compiler treats it a bit differently (this is
true for any lang item), I mean that it literally is treated as
<a href="http://manishearth.github.io/rust-internals-docs/rustc/ty/enum.TypeVariants.html#TyBox.v">a completely new kind of type</a>, not as a struct the way it has been defined in liballoc.
There&rsquo;s a TON of cruft in the compiler related to this type, much of which can be removed, but some
of which can&rsquo;t. If we ever do get <code>DerefMove</code>, we should probably try removing it all again. After
writing this post I&rsquo;m half-convinced to try and implement an internal-use-only <code>DerefMove</code> and try
cleaning up the code myself.</p>

<p>Most of this isn&rsquo;t really useful to know unless you actually come across a case where you can make
use of <code>DerefMove</code> semantics, or if you work on the compiler. But it certainly is interesting!</p>

<p>Next post: <a href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2017/01/11/rust-tidbits-what-is-a-lang-item/">What is a lang item?</a></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Seriously though, does anyone use it much? I&rsquo;ve only seen it getting used for boxed DSTs (trait objects and boxed slices), which themselves are pretty rare, for sending heap types over FFI, recursive types (rare), and random special cases. I find this pretty interesting given that other languages are much more liberal with non-refcounted single-element allocation.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>It will probably eventually be replaced or made equivalent to the <code>&lt;-</code> syntax before stabilizing<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>It&rsquo;s easier to special case the first two, much like how <code>for</code> loops are aware of the iterator trait without the iterator trait being extremely special cased<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on Rusting Trust]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2016/12/02/reflections-on-rusting-trust/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-02T11:28:27-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2016/12/02/reflections-on-rusting-trust</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Rust compiler is written in Rust. This is overall a pretty common practice in compiler
development. This usually means that the process of building the compiler involves downloading a
(typically) older version of the compiler.</p>

<p>This also means that the compiler is vulnerable to what is colloquially known as the &ldquo;Trusting
Trust&rdquo; attack, an attack described in <a href="https://www.ece.cmu.edu/~ganger/712.fall02/papers/p761-thompson.pdf">Ken Thompson&rsquo;s acceptance speech for the 1983 Turing Award</a>.
This kind of thing fascinates me, so I decided to try writing one myself. It&rsquo;s stuff like this which
started my interest in compilers, and I hope this post can help get others interested the same way.</p>

<p>To be clear, this isn&rsquo;t an indictment of Rust&rsquo;s security. Quite a few languages out there have
popular self-hosted compilers (C, C++, Haskell, Scala, D, Go) and are vulnerable to this attack. For
this attack to have any effect, one needs to be able to uniformly distribute this compiler, and
there are roughly equivalent ways of doing the same level of damage with that kind of access.</p>

<p>If you already know what a trusting trust attack is, you can skip the next section. If you just want
to see the code, it&rsquo;s in the <a href="https://github.com/Manishearth/rust/tree/rusting-trust">trusting-trust branch</a> on my Rust fork, specifically
<a href="https://github.com/Manishearth/rust/blob/rusting-trust/src/librustc_driver/driver.rs#L541">this code</a>.</p>

<h2>The attack</h2>

<p>The essence of the attack is this:</p>

<p>An attacker can conceivably change a compiler such that it can detect a particular kind of application and
make malicious changes to it. The example given in the talk was the UNIX <code>login</code> program &mdash; the attacker
can tweak a compiler so as to detect that it is compiling the <code>login</code> program, and compile in a
backdoor that lets it unconditionally accept a special password (created by the attacker) for any
user, thereby giving the attacker access to all accounts on all systems that have <code>login</code> compiled
by their modified compiler.</p>

<p>However, this change would be detected in the source. If it was not included in the source, this
change would disappear in the next release of the compiler, or when someone else compiles the
compiler from source. Avoiding this attack is easily done by compiling your own compilers and not
downloading untrusted binaries. This is good advice in general regarding untrusted binaries, and it
equally applies here.</p>

<p>To counter this, the attacker can go one step further. If they can tweak the compiler so as to
backdoor <code>login</code>, they could also tweak the compiler so as to backdoor itself. The attacker needs to
modify the compiler with a backdoor which detects when it is compiling the same compiler, and
introduces <em>itself</em> into the compiler that it is compiling. On top of this it can also introduce
backdoors into <code>login</code> or whatever other program the attacker is interested in.</p>

<p>Now, in this case, even if the backdoor is removed from the source, <em>every compiler compiled using
this backdoored compiler will be similarly backdoored</em>. So if this backdoored compiler somehow
starts getting distributed, it will spread itself as it is used to compile more copies of itself
(e.g. newer versions, etc). And it will be virtually undetectable &mdash; since the source doesn&rsquo;t
need to be modified for it to work; just the non-human-readable binary.</p>

<p>Of course, there are ways to protect against this. Ultimately, before a compiler for language X
existed, that compiler had to be written in some other language Y. If you can track the sources back
to that point you can bootstrap a working compiler from scratch and keep compiling newer compiler
versions till you reach the present. This raises the question of whether or not Y&rsquo;s compiler is
backdoored. While it sounds pretty unlikely that such a backdoor could be so robust as to work on
two different compilers and stay put throughout the history of X, you can of course trace back Y
back to other languages and so on till you find a compiler in assembly that you can verify<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<h2>Backdooring Rust</h2>

<p>Alright, so I want to backdoor my compiler. I first have to decide when in the pipeline the code
that insert backdoors executes. The Rust compiler operates by taking source code, parsing it into a
syntax tree (AST), transforming it into some intermediate representations (HIR and MIR), and feeding
it to LLVM in the form of LLVM IR, after which LLVM does its thing and creates binaries. A backdoor
can be inserted at any point in this stage. To me, it seems like it&rsquo;s easier to insert one into the
AST, because it&rsquo;s easier to obtain AST from source, and this is important as we&rsquo;ll see soon. It also
makes this attack less practically viable<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, which is nice since this is just a fun exercise and I
don&rsquo;t actually want to backdoor the compiler.</p>

<p>So the moment the compiler finishes parsing, my code will modify the AST to insert a backdoor.</p>

<p>First, I&rsquo;ll try to write a simpler backdoor; one which doesn&rsquo;t affect the compiler but instead
affects some programs. I shall write a backdoor that replaces occurrences of the string &ldquo;hello world&rdquo;
with &ldquo;जगाला नमस्कार&rdquo;, a rough translation of the same in my native language.</p>

<p>Now, in rustc, the <code>rustc_driver</code> crate is where the whole process of compiling is coordinated. In particular,
<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1cabe2151299c63497abc3a20bd08c04c0cd32a3/src/librustc_driver/driver.rs#L546"><code>phase_2_configure_and_expand</code></a> is run right after parsing (which is <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/blob/1cabe2151299c63497abc3a20bd08c04c0cd32a3/src/librustc_driver/driver.rs#L485">phase 1</a>). Perfect.
Within that function, the <code>krate</code> variable contains the parsed AST for the crate<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, and we need to modify that.</p>

<p>In this case, there&rsquo;s already machinery in <a href="http://manishearth.github.io/rust-internals-docs/syntax/fold/"><code>syntax::fold</code></a> for mutating ASTs based on patterns. A
<a href="http://manishearth.github.io/rust-internals-docs/syntax/fold/trait.Folder.html"><code>Folder</code></a> basically has the ability to walk the AST, producing a mirror AST, with modifications. For
each kind of node, you get to specify a function which will produce a node to be used in its place.
Most such functions will default to no-op (returning the same node).</p>

<p>So I write the following <code>Folder</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">// Understanding the minute details of this code isn't important; it is a bit complex
// since the API used here isn't meant to be used this way. Focus on the comments.

mod trust {
    use syntax::fold::*;
    use syntax::ast::*;
    use syntax::parse::token::InternedString;
    use syntax::ptr::P;
    struct TrustFolder;

    // The trait contains default impls which we override for specific cases
    impl Folder for TrustFolder {
        // every time we come across an expression, run this function
        // on it and replace it with the produced expression in the tree
        fn fold_expr(&amp;mut self, expr: P&lt;Expr&gt;) -&gt; P&lt;Expr&gt; {
            // The peculiar `.map` pattern needs to be used here
            // because of the way AST nodes are stored in immutable
            // `P&lt;T&gt;` pointers. The AST is not typically mutated.
            expr.map(|mut expr| {
                match expr.node {
                    ExprKind::Lit(ref mut l) =&gt; {
                        *l = l.clone().map(|mut l| {
                            // look for string literals
                            if let LitKind::Str(ref mut s, _) = l.node {
                                // replace their contents
                                if s == "hello world" {
                                    *s = InternedString::new("जगाला नमस्कार");
                                }
                            }
                            l
                        })
                    }
                    _ =&gt; ()
                }
                // recurse down expression with the default fold
                noop_fold_expr(expr, self)
            })
        }
        fn fold_mac(&amp;mut self, mac: Mac) -&gt; Mac {
            // Folders are not typically supposed to operate on pre-macro-expansion ASTs
            // and will by default panic here. We must explicitly specify otherwise.
            noop_fold_mac(mac, self)
        }
    }

    // our entry point
    pub fn fold_crate(krate: Crate) -&gt; Crate {
        // make a folder, fold the crate with it
        TrustFolder.fold_crate(krate)
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>I invoke it by calling <code>let krate = trust::fold_crate(krate);</code> as the first line of <code>phase_2_configure_and_expand</code>.</p>

<p>I create a stage 1 build<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> of rustc (<code>make rustc-stage1</code>). I&rsquo;ve already set up <code>rustup</code> to have a &ldquo;stage1&rdquo; toolchain
pointing to this folder (<code>rustup toolchain link stage1 /path/to/rust/target_triple/stage1</code>), so I can easily test this new compiler:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">// test.rs
fn main() {
    let x = "hello world";
    println!("{}", x);
}
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="sh">$ rustup run stage1 rustc test.rs
$ ./test
जगाला नमस्कार
</code></pre>

<p>Note that I had the string on a separate line instead of directly doing <code>println!("hello world")</code>.
This is because our backdoor isn&rsquo;t perfect; it applies to the <em>pre-expansion</em> AST. In this AST,
<code>println!</code> is stored as a macro and the <code>"hello world"</code> is part of the macro token tree; and has not
yet been turned into an expression. Our folder ignores it. It is not too hard to perform this same attack
post-expansion, however.</p>

<p>So far, so good. We have a compiler that tweaks &ldquo;hello world&rdquo; strings. Now, let&rsquo;s see if we can get
it to miscompile itself. This means that our compiler, when compiling a pristine Rust source tree,
should produce a compiler that is similarly backdoored (with the <code>trust</code> module and the
<code>trust::fold_crate()</code> call).</p>

<p>We need to tweak our folder so that it does two things:</p>

<ul>
<li>Inserts the <code>let krate = trust::fold_crate(krate);</code> statement in the appropriate function (<code>phase_2_configure_and_expand</code>) when compiling a pristine Rust source tree</li>
<li>Inserts the <code>trust</code> module</li>
</ul>


<p>The former is relatively easy. We need to construct an AST for that statement (can be done by
invoking the parser again and extracting the node). The latter is where it gets tricky. We can
encode instructions for outputting the AST of the <code>trust</code> module, but these instructions themselves
are within the same module, so the instructions for outputting <em>these</em> instructions need to be
included, and so on. This clearly isn&rsquo;t viable.</p>

<p>However, there&rsquo;s a way around this. It&rsquo;s a common trick used in writing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quine_(computing)">quines</a>, which face similar
issues. The idea is to put the entire block of code in a string. We then construct the code for the
module by doing something like</p>

<pre><code class="rust">mod trust {
    static SELF_STRING: &amp;'static str = "/* stringified contents of this module except for this line */";
    // ..
    fn fold_mod(..) {
        // ..
        // this produces a string that is the same as the code for the module containing it
        // SELF_STRING is used twice, once to produce the string literal for SELF_STRING, and
        // once to produce the code for the module
        let code_for_module = "mod trust { static SELF_STRING: &amp;'static str = \"" + SELF_STRING + "\";" + SELF_STRING + "}";
        insert_into_crate(code_for_module);
        // ..
    }
    // ..
}
</code></pre>

<p>With the code of the module entered in, this will look something like</p>

<pre><code class="rust">mod trust {
    static SELF_STRING: &amp;'static str = "
        // .. 
        fn fold_mod(..) {
            // ..
            // this produces a string that is the same as the code for the module containing it
            // SELF_STRING is used twice, once to produce the string literal for SELF_STRING, and
            // once to produce the code for the module
            let code_for_module = \"mod trust { static SELF_STRING: &amp;'static str = \\\"\" + SELF_STRING + \"\\\";\" + SELF_STRING + \"}\";
            insert_into_crate(code_for_module);
            // ..
        }
        // ..
    ";

    // ..
    fn fold_mod(..) {
        // ..
        // this produces a string that is the same as the code for the module containing it
        // SELF_STRING is used twice, once to produce the string literal for SELF_STRING, and
        // once to produce the code for the module
        let code_for_module = "mod trust { static SELF_STRING: &amp;'static str = \"" + SELF_STRING + "\";" + SELF_STRING + "}";
        insert_into_crate(code_for_module);
        // ..
    }
    // ..
}
</code></pre>

<p>So you have a string containing the contents of the module, except for itself. You build the code
for the module by using the string twice &ndash; once to construct the code for the declaration of the
string, and once to construct the code for the rest of the module. Now, by parsing this, you&rsquo;ll get
the original AST!</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s try this step by step. Let&rsquo;s first see if injecting an arbitrary string (<code>use foo::bar::blah</code>)
works, without worrying about this cyclical quineyness:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">mod trust {
    // dummy string just to see if it gets injected
    // inserting the full code of this module has some practical concerns
    // about escaping which I'll address later
    static SELF_STRING: &amp;'static str = "use foo::bar::blah;";
    use syntax::fold::*;
    use syntax::ast::*;
    use syntax::parse::parse_crate_from_source_str;
    use syntax::parse::token::InternedString;
    use syntax::ptr::P;
    use syntax::util::move_map::MoveMap;
    use rustc::session::Session;

    struct TrustFolder&lt;'a&gt; {
        // we need the session to be able to parse things. No biggie.
        sess: &amp;'a Session,
    }

    impl&lt;'a&gt; Folder for TrustFolder&lt;'a&gt; {
        fn fold_expr(&amp;mut self, expr: P&lt;Expr&gt;) -&gt; P&lt;Expr&gt; {
            expr.map(|mut expr| {
                match expr.node {
                    ExprKind::Lit(ref mut l) =&gt; {
                        *l = l.clone().map(|mut l| {
                            if let LitKind::Str(ref mut s, _) = l.node {
                                if s == "hello world" {
                                    *s = InternedString::new("जगाला नमस्कार");
                                }
                            }
                            l
                        })
                    }
                    _ =&gt; ()
                }
                noop_fold_expr(expr, self)
            })
        }
        fn fold_mod(&amp;mut self, m: Mod) -&gt; Mod {
            // move_flat_map takes a vector, constructs a new one by operating
            // on each element by-move. Again, needed because of `P&lt;T&gt;`
            let new_items = m.items.move_flat_map(|item| {
                // we want to modify this function, and give it a sibling from SELF_STRING
                if item.ident.name.as_str() == "phase_2_configure_and_expand" {
                    // parse SELF_STRING
                    let new_crate = parse_crate_from_source_str("trust".into(),
                                                                SELF_STRING.into(),
                                                                &amp;self.sess.parse_sess).unwrap();
                    // extract the first item contained in it, which is the use statement
                    let inner_item = new_crate.module.items[0].clone();

                    // move_flat_map needs an iterator of items to insert
                    vec![inner_item, item].into_iter()
                } else {
                    vec![item].into_iter()
                }
            });
            let m = Mod {
                inner: m.inner,
                items: new_items,
            };
            noop_fold_mod(m, self)
        }
        fn fold_mac(&amp;mut self, _mac: Mac) -&gt; Mac {
            noop_fold_mac(_mac, self)
        }
    }

    pub fn fold_crate(krate: Crate, sess: &amp;Session) -&gt; Crate {
        let mut folder = TrustFolder {sess: sess};
        folder.fold_crate(krate)
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>We also change the original call in <code>phase_2_configure_and_expand</code> to <code>let krate = trust::fold_crate(krate, sess);</code></p>

<p>Compiling with <code>make rustc-stage2</code> (we now want the backdoored stage1 compiler to try and compile
the same sources and fudge the <code>phase_2_configure_and_expand</code> function the second time around), gets us this error:</p>

<pre><code>rustc: x86_64-apple-darwin/stage1/lib/rustlib/x86_64-apple-darwin/lib/librustc_driver
error[E0432]: unresolved import `foo::bar::blah`
 --&gt; trust:1:5
  |
1 | use foo::bar::blah;
  |     ^^^^^^^^^^^^^^ Maybe a missing `extern crate foo;`?

error: aborting due to previous error
</code></pre>

<p>This is exactly what we expected! We inserted the code <code>use foo::bar::blah;</code>, which isn&rsquo;t going to
resolve, and thus got a failure when compiling the crate the second time around.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s add the code for the quineyness and for inserting the <code>fold_crate</code> call:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">fn fold_mod(&amp;mut self, m: Mod) -&gt; Mod {
    let new_items = m.items.move_flat_map(|item| {
        // look for the phase_2_configure_and_expand function
        if item.ident.name.as_str() == "phase_2_configure_and_expand" {
            // construct the code for the module contents as described earlier
            let code_for_module = r###"mod trust { static SELF_STRING: &amp;'static str = r##"###.to_string() + r###"##""### + SELF_STRING + r###""##"### + r###"##;"### + SELF_STRING + "}";
            // Parse it into an AST by creating a crate only containing that code
            let new_crate = parse_crate_from_source_str("trust".into(),
                                                        code_for_module,
                                                        &amp;self.sess.parse_sess).unwrap();
            // extract the AST of the contained module
            let inner_mod = new_crate.module.items[0].clone();

            // now to insert the fold_crate() call
            let item = item.map(|mut i| {
                if let ItemKind::Fn(.., ref mut block) = i.node {
                    *block = block.clone().map(|mut b| {
                        // create a temporary crate just containing a fold_crate call
                        let new_crate = parse_crate_from_source_str("trust".into(),
                                                                    "fn trust() {let krate = trust::fold_crate(krate, sess);}".into(),
                                                                    &amp;self.sess.parse_sess).unwrap();
                        // extract the AST from the parsed temporary crate, shove it in here
                        if let ItemKind::Fn(.., ref blk) = new_crate.module.items[0].node {
                            b.stmts.insert(0, blk.stmts[0].clone());
                        }
                        b
                    });
                }
                i
            });
            // yield both the created module and the modified function to move_flat_map
            vec![inner_mod, item].into_iter()
        } else {
            vec![item].into_iter()
        }
    });
    let m = Mod {
        inner: m.inner,
        items: new_items,
    };
    noop_fold_mod(m, self)
}
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>#</code>s let us specify &ldquo;raw strings&rdquo; in Rust, where I can freely include other quotation marks
without needing to escape things. For a string starting with <code>n</code> pound symbols, we can have raw
strings with up to <code>n - 1</code> pound symbols inside it. The <code>SELF_STRING</code> is declared with four pound
symbols, and the code in the trust module only uses raw strings with three pound symbols. Since the
code needs to generate the declaration of <code>SELF_STRING</code> (with four pound symbols), we manually
concatenate extra pound symbols on &ndash; a 4-pound-symbol raw string will not be valid within a three-
pound-symbol raw string since the parser will try to end the string early. So we don&rsquo;t ever directly
type a sequence of four consecutive pound symbols in the code, and instead construct it by
concatenating two pairs of pound symbols.</p>

<p>Ultimately, the <code>code_for_module</code> declaration really does the same as:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">let code_for_module = "mod trust { static SELF_STRING: &amp;'static str = \"" + SELF_STRING + "\";" + SELF_STRING + "}";
</code></pre>

<p>conceptually, but also ensures that things stay escaped. I could get similar results by calling into
a function that takes a string and inserts literal backslashes at the appropriate points.</p>

<p>To update <code>SELF_STRING</code>, we just need to include all the code inside the <code>trust</code> module after the
declaration of <code>SELF_STRING</code> itself inside the string. I won&rsquo;t include this inline since it&rsquo;s big,
but <a href="https://github.com/Manishearth/rust/blob/rusting-trust/src/librustc_driver/driver.rs#L541">this is what it looks like in the end</a>.</p>

<p>If we try compiling this code to stage 2 after updating <code>SELF_STRING</code>, we will get errors about
duplicate <code>trust</code> modules, which makes sense because we&rsquo;re actually already compiling an already-
backdoored version of the Rust source code. While we could set up two Rust builds, the easiest way
to verify if our attack is working is to just use <code>#[cfg(stage0)]</code> on the trust module and the
<code>fold_crate</code> call<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>. These will only get included during &ldquo;stage 0&rdquo; (when it compiles the stage 1
compiler<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>), and not when it compiles the stage 2 compiler, so if the stage 2 compiler still
backdoors executables, we&rsquo;re done.</p>

<p>On building the stage 2 (<code>make rustc-stage2</code>) compiler,</p>

<pre><code class="sh">$ rustup run stage2 rustc test.rs
$ ./test
जगाला नमस्कार
</code></pre>

<p>I was also able to make it work with a separate clone of Rust:</p>

<pre><code class="sh">$ cd /path/to/new/clone
# Tell rustup to use our backdoored stage1 compiler whenever rustc is invoked
# from anywhere inside this folder.
$ rustup override set stage1 # Works with stage 2 as well.

# with --enable-local-rust, instead of the downloaded stage 0 compiler compiling
# stage 0 internal libraries (like libsyntax), the libraries from the local Rust get used. Hence we
# need to check out a git commit close to our changes. This commit is the parent of our changes,
# and is bound to work
$ git checkout bfa709a38a8c607e1c13ee5635fbfd1940eb18b1

# This will make it call `rustc` instead of downloading its own compiler.
# We already overrode rustc to be our backdoored compiler for this folder
# using rustup
$ ./configure --enable-local-rust
# build it!
$ make rustc-stage1
# Tell rustup about the new toolchain
$ rustup toolchain link other-stage1 /path/to/new/clone/target_dir/stage1
$ rustup run other-stage1 rustc test.rs
$ ./test
जगाला नमस्कार
</code></pre>

<p>Thus, a pristine copy of the rustc source has built a compiler infected with the backdoor.</p>

<hr />

<p>So we now have a working trusting trust attack in Rust. What can we do with it? Hopefully nothing!
This particular attack isn&rsquo;t very robust, and while that can be improved upon, building a practical
and resilient trusting trust attack that won&rsquo;t get noticed is a bit trickier.</p>

<p>We in the Rust community should be working on ways to prevent such attacks from being successful, though.</p>

<p>A couple of things we could do are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Work on an alternate Rust compiler (in Rust or otherwise). For a pair of self-hosted compilers, there&rsquo;s a technique called <a href="http://www.acsa-admin.org/countering-trusting-trust-through-diverse-double-compiling/">&ldquo;Diverse Double-Compiling&rdquo;</a> wherein you choose an arbitrary sequence of compilers (something like &ldquo;<code>gcc</code> followed by 3x <code>clang</code> followed by <code>gcc</code>&rdquo; followed by <code>clang</code>), and compile each compiler with the output of the previous one. Difficulty of writing a backdoor that can survive this process grows exponentially.</li>
<li>Try compiling rustc from its ocaml roots, and package up the process into a shell script so that you have reproducible trustworthy rustc builds.</li>
<li>Make rustc builds deterministic, which means that a known-trustworthy rustc build can be compared against a suspect one to figure out if it has been tampered with.</li>
</ul>


<p>Overall trusting trust attacks aren&rsquo;t that pressing a concern since there are many other ways to get
approximately equivalent access with the same threat model. Having the ability to insert any
backdoor into distributed binaries is bad enough, and should be protected against regardless of
whether or not the backdoor is a self-propagating one. If someone had access to the distribution or
build servers, for example, they could as easily insert a backdoor into the <em>server</em>, or place a key
so that they can reupload tampered binaries when they want. Now, cleaning up after these attacks is
easier than trusting trust, but ultimately this is like comparing being at the epicenter of Little
Boy or the Tsar Bomba &ndash; one is worse, but you&rsquo;re atomized regardless, and your mitigation plan
shouldn&rsquo;t need to change.</p>

<p>But it&rsquo;s certainly an interesting attack, and should be something we should at least be thinking
about.</p>

<p><em>Thanks to Josh Matthews, Michael Layzell, Diane Hosfelt, Eevee, and Yehuda Katz for reviewing drafts of this post.</em></p>

<p><small>Discuss: <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=13091941">HN</a>, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/rust/comments/5g5hib/reflections_on_rusting_trust/">Reddit</a></small></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Of course, <em>this</em> raises the question of whether or not your assembler/OS/loader/processor is backdoored. Ultimately, you have to trust <em>someone</em>, which was partly the point of Thompson&rsquo;s talk.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>The AST turns up in the metadata/debuginfo/error messages, can be inspected from the command line, and in general is very far upstream and affects a number of things (all the other stages in the pipeline). You could write code to strip it out from these during inspection and only have it turn up in the binary, but that is much harder.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>The local variable is called <code>krate</code> because <code>crate</code> is a keyword<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Stage 1 takes the downloaded (older) rust compiler and compiles the sources from it. The stage 2 compiler is build when the stage 1 compiler (which is a &ldquo;new&rdquo; compiler) is used to compile the sources again.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>Using it on the <code>fold_crate</code> call requires enabling the &ldquo;attributes on statements&rdquo; feature, but that&rsquo;s no big deal &ndash; we&rsquo;re only using the cfgs to be able to test easily; this feature won&rsquo;t actually be required if we use our stage1 compiler to compile a clean clone of the sources.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>The numbering of the stages is a bit confusing. During &ldquo;stage 0&rdquo; (<code>cfg(stage0)</code>), the stage 1 compiler is <em>built</em>. Since you are building the stage 1 compiler, the make invocation is <code>make rustc-stage1</code>. Similarly, during stage 1, the stage 2 compiler is built, and the invocation is <code>make rustc-stage2</code> but you use <code>#[cfg(stage1)]</code> in the code.<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Designing a GC in Rust]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2015/09/01/designing-a-gc-in-rust/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-01T01:23:40-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2015/09/01/designing-a-gc-in-rust</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a while I&rsquo;ve been working on a <a href="http://github.com/Manishearth/rust-gc/">garbage collector for Rust</a> with <a href="http://github.com/mystor">Michael
Layzell</a>. I thought this would be a good time to talk of our design and progress so far.</p>

<h1>Motivation</h1>

<p>&ldquo;Wait&rdquo;, you ask, &ldquo;why does Rust need a garbage collector&rdquo;? Rust is supposed to work <em>without</em> a GC,
that&rsquo;s one of its main selling points!</p>

<p>True. Rust <em>does</em> work pretty well without a GC. It&rsquo;s managed to do without one so far, and we still
have all sorts of well-written crates out there (none of which use a GC).</p>

<p>But Rust is not just about low-cost memory safety. It&rsquo;s also <a href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2015/05/27/wrapper-types-in-rust-choosing-your-guarantees/">about choosing your costs and
guarantees</a>. <code>Box&lt;T&gt;</code> and stack allocation are not always sufficient, sometimes one needs to
reach for something like <code>Rc&lt;T&gt;</code> (reference counting). But even <code>Rc</code> is not perfect; it can&rsquo;t handle
cycles between pointers. There are solutions to that issue like using <code>Weak&lt;T&gt;</code>, but that only works
in limited cases (when you know what the points-to graph looks like at compile time), and isn&rsquo;t very
ergonomic.</p>

<p>Cases where one needs to maintain a complicated, dynamic graph are where a GC becomes useful.
Similarly, if one is writing an interpreter for a GCd language, having a GC in Rust would simplify
things a lot.</p>

<p>Not to say that one should pervasively use a GC in Rust. Similar to <code>Rc&lt;T&gt;</code>, it&rsquo;s best to use
regular ownership-based memory management as much as possible, and sprinkle <code>Rc</code>/<code>Gc</code> in places
where your code needs it.</p>

<h1>Previous designs</h1>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t the first GC in Rust. Automatic memory management has existed before in various forms,
but all were limited.</p>

<p>Besides the ones listed below, Nick Fitzgerald&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/fitzgen/bacon-rajan-cc">cycle collector</a> based on <a href="researcher.watson.ibm.com/researcher/files/us-bacon/Bacon01Concurrent.pdf">this paper</a>
exists and is something that you should look into if you&rsquo;re interested. There&rsquo;s also <a href="https://github.com/pliniker/mo-gc/blob/master/doc/Project-RFC.md">an RFC</a>
by Peter Liniker which sketches out a design for an immutable GC.</p>

<h2>Core Rust GC(s)</h2>

<p>Rust itself had a garbage collector until a bit more than a year ago. These &ldquo;managed pointers&rdquo;
(<code>@T</code>) were part of the language. They were removed later with a plan to make GC a library feature.</p>

<p>I believe these were basically reference counted (cycle collected?) pointers with some language
integration, but I&rsquo;m not sure.</p>

<p>Nowadays, the only form of automatic memory management in Rust are via <a href="http://doc.rust-lang.org/alloc/rc/struct.Rc.html"><code>Rc</code></a> and <a href="http://doc.rust-lang.org/std/sync/struct.Arc.html"><code>Arc</code></a>
which are nonatomic and atomic reference counted pointers respectively. In other words, they keep
track of the number of shared references via a reference count (incremented when it is cloned,
decremented when destructors run). If the reference count reaches zero, the contents are cleaned up.</p>

<p>This is a pretty useful abstraction, however, as mentioned above, it doesn&rsquo;t let you create cycles
without leaking them.</p>

<h2>Spidermonkey</h2>

<p><em>You can read more about Servo&rsquo;s Spidermonkey bindings <a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/research/2014/08/26/javascript-servos-only-garbage-collector/">in this blog post</a> (somewhat
outdated, but still relevant)</em></p>

<p>In Servo we use <a href="http://github.com/servo/rust-mozjs/">bindings to the Spidermonkey Javascript engine</a>. Since Javascript is a
garbage collected language, the Rust representations of Javascript objects are also garbage
collected.</p>

<p>Of course, this sort of GC isn&rsquo;t really useful for generic use since it comes bundled with a JS
runtime. However, the Rust side of the GC is of a design that could be used in an independent
library.</p>

<p>The Rust side of the Spidermonkey GC is done through a bunch of smart pointers, and a trait called
<code>JSTraceable</code>. <code>JSTraceable</code> is a trait which can &ldquo;trace&rdquo; recursively down some data, finding and
marking all GC-managed objects inside it. This is autoderived using Rust&rsquo;s plugin infrastructure, so
a simple <code>#[jstraceable]</code> annotation will generate trace hooks for the struct it is on.</p>

<p>Now, we have various smart pointers. The first is <code>JS&lt;T&gt;</code>. This is opaque, but can be held by other
GC-managed structs. To use this on the stack, this must be explicitly <em>rooted</em>, via <code>.root()</code>. This
produces a <code>Root&lt;T&gt;</code>, which can be dereferenced to get the inner object. When the <code>Root</code> is created,
the contained object is listed in a collection of &ldquo;roots&rdquo; in a global. A root indicates that the
value is being used on the stack somewhere, and the GC starts tracing usage from these roots. When
the <code>Root&lt;T&gt;</code> is destroyed, the root is removed.</p>

<p>The problem with this is that <code>JS&lt;T&gt;</code> doesn&rsquo;t work on the stack. There is no way for the GC to know
that we are holding on to <code>JS&lt;T&gt;</code> on the stack. So, if I copy a <code>JS&lt;T&gt;</code> to the stack, remove all
references to it from objects in the GC heap, and trigger a collection, the <code>JS&lt;T&gt;</code> will still be
around on the stack after collection since the GC can&rsquo;t trace to it. If I attempt to root it, I may
get a panic or a segfault depending on the implementation.</p>

<p>To protect against this, we have a bunch of lints. The <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/blob/master/components/plugins/lints/unrooted_must_root.rs">relevant one</a> here protects
against <code>JS&lt;T&gt;</code> from being carried around on the stack; but like most lints, it&rsquo;s not perfect.</p>

<p>To summarize: Spidermonkey gives us a good GC. However using it for a generic Rust program is ill
advised. Additionally, Servo&rsquo;s wrappers around the GC are cheap, but need lints for safety. While it
would probably be possible to write safer wrappers for general usage, it&rsquo;s pretty impractical to
carry around a JS runtime when you don&rsquo;t need one.</p>

<p>However, Spidermonkey&rsquo;s GC did inspire me to think more into the matter.</p>

<h1>Brainstorming a design</h1>

<p>For quite a while I&rsquo;d had various ideas about GCs. Most were simplifications of Servo&rsquo;s wrappers
(there&rsquo;s some complexity brought in there by Spidermonkey that&rsquo;s not necessary for a general GC).
Most were tracing/rooting with mark-and-sweep collection. All of them used lints. Being rather busy,
I didn&rsquo;t really work on it past that, but planned to work on it if I could find someone to work
with.</p>

<p>One day, <a href="http://github.com/mystor">Michael</a> pinged me on IRC and asked me about GCs. Lots of people knew that I was
interested in writing a GC for Rust, and one of them directed him to me when he expressed a similar
interest.</p>

<p>So we started discussing GCs. We settled on a tracing mark-and-sweep GC. In other words, the GC runs
regular &ldquo;sweeps&rdquo; where it first &ldquo;traces&rdquo; the usage of all objects and marks them and their children
as used, and then sweeps up all unused objects.</p>

<p>This model on its own has a flaw. It doesn&rsquo;t know about GC pointers held on the stack as local
variables (&ldquo;stack roots&rdquo;). There are multiple methods for solving this. We&rsquo;ve already seen one above
in the Spidermonkey design &ndash; maintain two types of pointers (one for the stack, one for the heap),
and try very hard using static analysis to ensure that they don&rsquo;t cross over.</p>

<p>A common model (used by GCs like Boehm, called &ldquo;conservative GCs&rdquo;) is to do something called &ldquo;stack
scanning&rdquo;. In such a system, the GC goes down the stack looking for things which may perhaps be GC
pointers. Generally the GC allocates objects in known regions of the memory, so a GC pointer is any
value on the stack which belongs to one of these regions.</p>

<p>Of course, this makes garbage collection rather inefficient, and will miss cases like <code>Box&lt;Gc&lt;T&gt;&gt;</code>
where the GCd pointer is accessible, but through a non-GC pointer.</p>

<p>We decided rather early on that we didn&rsquo;t want a GC based on lints or stack scanning. Both are
rather suboptimal solutions in my opinion, and very hard to make sound<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. We were also hoping that
Rust&rsquo;s type system and ownership semantics could help us in designing a good, safe, API.</p>

<p>So, we needed a way to keep track of roots, and we needed a way to trace objects.</p>

<h2>Tracing</h2>

<p>The latter part was easy. We wrote a compiler plugin (well, we stole <a href="https://github.com/servo/servo/blob/master/components/plugins/jstraceable.rs#L38">Servo&rsquo;s tracing plugin which
I&rsquo;d written earlier</a>) which autoderives an implementation of the <code>Trace</code> trait on any
given struct or enum, using the same internal infrastructure that <code>#[derive(PartialEq)]</code> and the
rest use. So, with just the following code, it&rsquo;s easy to make a struct or enum gc-friendly:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">#[derive(Trace)]
struct Foo {
    x: u8,
    y: Bar,
}

#[derive(Trace)]
enum Bar {
    Baz(u8), Quux
}
</code></pre>

<p>For a <code>foo</code> of type <code>Foo</code> <code>foo.trace()</code>, will expand to a call of <code>foo.x.trace()</code> and
<code>foo.y.trace()</code>. <code>bar.trace()</code> will check which variant it is and call <code>trace()</code> on the <code>u8</code> inside
if it&rsquo;s a <code>Baz</code>. For most structs this turns out to be a no-op and is often optimized away by
inlining, but if a struct contains a <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code>, the special implementation of <code>Trace</code> for <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code> will
&ldquo;mark&rdquo; the traceability of the <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code>. Types without <code>Trace</code> implemented cannot be used in types
implementing <code>Trace</code> or in a <code>Gc</code>, which is enforced with a <code>T: Trace</code> bound on <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code>.</p>

<p>So, we have a way of walking the fields of a given object and finding inner <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code>s. Splendid. This
lets us write the mark&amp;sweep phase easily: Take the list of known reachable <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code>s, walk their
contents until you find more <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code>s (marking all you find), and clean up any which aren&rsquo;t
reachable.</p>

<h2>Rooting</h2>

<p>Of course, now we have to solve the problem of keeping track of the known reachable <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code>s, i.e.
the roots. This is a hard problem to solve without language support, and I hope that eventually we
might be able to get the language hooks necessary to solve it. LLVM <a href="http://llvm.org/docs/GarbageCollection.html#gcroot">has support for tracking
GCthings on the stack</a>, and some day we may be able to leverage that in Rust.</p>

<p>As noted above, Spidermonkey&rsquo;s solution was to have non-rooted (non-dereferencable) heap pointers,
which can be explicitly converted to rooted pointers and then read.</p>

<p>We went the other way. All <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code> pointers, when created, are considered &ldquo;rooted&rdquo;. The instance of
<code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code> has a &ldquo;rooted&rdquo; bit set to true, and the underlying shared box (<code>GcBox</code>, though this is not a
public interface) has its &ldquo;root count&rdquo; set to one.</p>

<p>When this <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code> is cloned, an identical <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code> (with rooted bit set to true) is returned, and the
underlying root count is incremented. Cloning a <code>Gc</code> does not perform a deep copy.</p>

<pre><code class="rust">let a = Gc::new(20); // a.root = true, (*a.ptr).roots = 1, (*a.ptr).data = 20

// ptr points to the underlying box, which contains the data as well as
// GC metadata like the root count. `Gc::new()` will allocate this box

let b = a.clone(); // b.root = true, (*a.ptr).roots++, b.ptr = a.ptr
</code></pre>

<p>This is rather similar to how <code>Rc</code> works, however there is no <code>root</code> field, and the <code>roots</code> counter
is called a &ldquo;reference counter&rdquo;.</p>

<p>For regular local sharing, it is recommended to just use a borrowed reference to the inner variable
(borrowing works fine with rust-gc!) since there is no cost to creating this reference.</p>

<p>When a GC thing is put inside another GC thing, the first thing no longer can remain a root. This is
handled by &ldquo;unrooting&rdquo; the first GC thing:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">struct Foo {
    bar: u32,
    baz: Gc&lt;u32&gt;,
}

let a = Gc::new(20); // why anyone would want to GC an integer I'll never know
                     // but I'll stick with this example since it's simple

let b = Gc::new(Foo {bar: 1, baz: a});
// a.root = false, (*a.ptr).roots--
// b initialized similar to previous example

// `a` was moved into `b`, so now `a` cannot be accessed directly here
// other than through `b`, and `a` is no longer a root.
// To avoid moving a, passing `a.clone()` to `b` will work
</code></pre>

<p>Of course, we need a way to traverse the object passed to the <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code>, in this case <code>Foo</code>, and look
for any contained <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code>s to unroot. Sound familiar? This needs the same mechanism that <code>trace()</code>
needed! We add struct-walking <code>root()</code> and <code>unroot()</code> methods to the <code>Trace</code> trait which are auto-
derived exactly the same way, and continue. (We don&rsquo;t need <code>root()</code> right now, but we will need it
later on).</p>

<p>Now, during collection, we can just traverse the list of <code>GcBox</code>s and use the ones with a nonzero
root count as roots for our mark traversal.</p>

<p>So far, so good. We have a pretty sound design for a GC that works &hellip; for immutable data.</p>

<h3>Mutability</h3>

<p>Like <code>Rc&lt;T&gt;</code>, <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code> is by default immutable. Rust abhors aliasable mutability, <a href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2015/05/17/the-problem-with-shared-mutability/">even in single
threaded contexts</a>, and both these smart pointers allow aliasing.</p>

<p>Mutation poses a problem for our GC, beyond the regular problems of aliasable mutability: It&rsquo;s
possible to move rooted things into heap objects and vice versa:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">let x = Gc::new(20);

let y = Gc::new(None);

*y = Some(x); // uh oh, x is still considered rooted!

// and the reverse!

let y = Gc::new(Some(Gc::new(20)));

let x = y.take(); // x was never rooted!
// `take()` moves the `Some(Gc&lt;u32&gt;)` out of `y`, replaces it with `None`       
</code></pre>

<p>Since <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code> doesn&rsquo;t implement <code>DerefMut</code>, none of this is possible &mdash; one cannot mutate the
inner data. This is one of the places where Rust&rsquo;s ownership/mutability system works out awesomely
in our favor.</p>

<p>Of course, an immutable GC isn&rsquo;t very useful. We can&rsquo;t even create cycles in an immutable GC, so why
would anyone need this in the first place<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>?</p>

<p>So of course, we needed to make it somehow mutable. People using <code>Rc&lt;T&gt;</code> solve this problem by using
<code>RefCell&lt;T&gt;</code>, which maintains something similar to the borrow semantics at runtime and is internally
mutable. <code>RefCell&lt;T&gt;</code> itself can&rsquo;t be used by us since it doesn&rsquo;t guard against the problem
illustrated above (and hence won&rsquo;t implement <code>Trace</code>, but a similar cell type would work).</p>

<p>So we created <code>GcCell&lt;T&gt;</code>. This behaves just like <code>RefCell&lt;T&gt;</code>, except that it will <code>root()</code> before
beginning a mutable borrow, and <code>unroot()</code> before ending it (well, only if it itself is not rooted,
which is tracked by an internal field similar to <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code>). Now, everything is safe:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">#[derive(Trace)]
struct Foo {
    a: u8,
    b: GcCell&lt;Gc&lt;u8&gt;&gt;,
}

let x = Gc::new(20);

let y = Gc::new(Foo {a: 10, b: Gc::new(30)});
{
    *y.b.borrow_mut() = x; // the `Gc(30)` from `y.b` was rooted by this call
                           // but since we don't actually use it here,
                           // the destructor gets rid of it.
                           // We could use swap() to retain access to it.
    // ...
    // x unrooted
}


// and the reverse case works too:

let y = Gc::new(GcCell::new(Some(Gc::new(20))));

let x = y.borrow_mut().take(); // the inner `Some(Gc(20))` gets rooted by `borrow_mut()`
                               // before `x` can access it
</code></pre>

<p>So now, mutation works too! We have a working garbage collector!</p>

<h1>Open problems</h1>

<h2>Destructors</h2>

<p>I believe this can be solved without lints, but it <em>may</em> require some upcoming features of Rust to
be implemented first (like specialization).</p>

<p>In essence, destructors implemented on a value inside <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code> can be unsafe. This will only happen
if they try to access values within a <code>Gc&lt;T&gt;</code> &mdash; if they do, they may come across a box that
has already been collected, or they may lengthen the lifetime of a box scheduled to be collected.</p>

<p>The basic solution to this is to use &ldquo;finalizers&rdquo; instead of destructors. Finalizers, like in Java,
are not guaranteed to run. However, we may need further drop hooks or trait specialization to make
an airtight interface for this. I don&rsquo;t have a concrete design for this yet, though.</p>

<h2>Concurrency</h2>

<p>Our model mostly just works in a concurrent situation (with thread safety tweaks, of course); in
fact it&rsquo;s possible to make it so that the concurrent GC will not &ldquo;stop the world&rdquo; unless someone
tries to do a write to a <code>GcCell</code>. We have an experimental concurrent GC in <a href="https://github.com/Manishearth/rust-gc/pull/6">this pull
request</a>. We still need to figure out how to make interop between both GCs safe, though we may
just end up making them such that an object using one GC cannot be fed to an object using the other.</p>

<h2>Performance</h2>

<p>So far we haven&rsquo;t really focused on performance, and worked on ensuring safety. Our collection
triggering algorithm, for example, was horribly inefficient, though we planned on improving it. The
wonderful Huon <a href="https://github.com/Manishearth/rust-gc/pull/9">fixed this</a>, though.</p>

<p>Similarly, we haven&rsquo;t yet optimized storage. We have some ideas which we may work on later. (If you
want to help, contributions welcome!)</p>

<h2>Cross-crate deriving</h2>

<p>Currently, an object deriving <code>Trace</code> should have <code>Trace</code>able children. This isn&rsquo;t always possible
when members from another crate (which does not depend on rust-gc) are involved. At the moment, we
allow an <code>#[unsafe_ignore_trace]</code> annotation on fields which are of this type (which excludes it
from being traced &ndash; if that crate doesn&rsquo;t transitively depend on rust-gc, its members cannot
contain GCthings anyway unless generics are involved). It should be possible to detect whether or
not this is safe, and/or autoderive <code>Trace</code> using the opt-in builtin traits framework (needs
specialization to work), but at the moment we don&rsquo;t do anything other than expose that annotation.</p>

<p>Stdlib support for a global <code>Trace</code> trait that everyone derives would be awesome.</p>

<h1>Conclusion</h1>

<p>Designing a GC was a wonderful experience! I didn&rsquo;t get to write much code (I was busy and Michael
was able to implement most of it overnight because he&rsquo;s totally awesome), but the long design
discussions followed by trying to figure out holes in the GC design in every idle moment of the day
were quite enjoyable. GCs are very hard to get right, but it&rsquo;s very satisfying when you come up with
a design that works! I&rsquo;m also quite happy at how well Rust helped in making a safe interface.</p>

<p>I encourage everyone to try it out and/or find holes in our design. Contributions of all kind
welcome, we&rsquo;d especially love performance improvements and testcases.</p>

<p><small>Discuss: <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=10148471">HN</a>, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/rust/comments/3j4bx2/designing_a_gc_in_rust/">Reddit</a></small></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I&rsquo;m very skeptical that it&rsquo;s possible to make either of these completely sound without writing lints which effectively rewrite a large chunk of the compiler<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>There is a case to be made for an immutable GC which allows some form of deferred initialization of GC fields, however.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
