<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: C++ | In Pursuit of Laziness]]></title>
  <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/categories/c-plus-plus/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2021-03-30T17:33:37+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://manishearth.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Manish Goregaokar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Integrating Rust and C++ in Firefox]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2021/02/22/integrating-rust-and-c-plus-plus-in-firefox/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2021/02/22/integrating-rust-and-c-plus-plus-in-firefox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post was originally drafted in August 2018, but I never got around to finishing it. As such, parts of its framing (e.g. the focus on bindgen) are outdated, given the relative infancy of the interop space at the time. I was recently told that the post is still useful in this form so I decided to finish and publish it anyway, while attempting to mark outdated things as such when I notice them. Everything after the allocators section was written near the time of publication.</em></p>

<p>In 2017 I worked on the <a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2017/08/inside-a-super-fast-css-engine-quantum-css-aka-stylo/">Stylo</a> project, uplifting Servo’s CSS engine (“style system”) into Firefox’s browser engine
(“Gecko”). This involved a <em>lot</em> of gnarly FFI between Servo’s Rust codebase and Firefox’s C++ codebase. There were a
lot of challenges in doing this, and I feel like it’s worth sharing things from our experiences.</p>

<p>If you’re interested in Rust integrations, you may find <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x9acx2zgx4Q">this talk by Katharina on Rust - C++ FFI</a>, and <a href="https://hsivonen.fi/modern-cpp-in-rust/">this blog post by Henri on integrating encoding-rs into Firefox</a> useful as well.</p>

<h2 id="who-is-this-post-for">Who is this post for?</h2>

<p>So, first off the bat, I’ll mention that when integrating Rust into a C++ codebase, you
want to <em>avoid</em> having integrations as tight as Stylo. Don’t do what we did; make your Rust
component mostly self-contained so that you just have to maintain something like ten FFI functions
for interacting with it. If this is possible to do, you should do it and your life will be <em>much</em> easier. Pick a clean API boundary, define a straightforward API, use cbindgen or bindgen if necessary without any tricks, and you should be good to go.</p>

<p>That said, sometimes you <em>have</em> to have gnarly integrations, and this blog post is for those use cases.
These techniques mostly use bindgen in their examples, however you can potentially use them with hand-rolled bindings or another tool as well. If you’re at this level of complexity, however, the potential for mistakes in the hand-rolled bindings is probably not worth it.</p>

<p><em>Note from 2021: <a href="https://github.com/dtolnay/cxx">cxx</a> is probably a better tool for many of the use cases here, though many of the techniques still transfer.</em></p>

<h2 id="what-was-involved-in-stylos-ffi">What was involved in Stylo’s FFI?</h2>

<p>So, what made Stylo’s FFI so complicated?</p>

<p>It turns out that browsers are quite monolithic. You can split them into vaguely-defined components, but
these components are still tightly integrated. If you intend to replace a component, you may need to
make a jagged edge of an integration surface.</p>

<p>The style system is more self-contained than other parts, but it’s still quite tightly integrated.</p>

<p>The main job of a “style system” is to take the CSS rules and DOM tree, and run them through “the cascade”<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">1</a></sup>
with an output of “computed styles” tagged on each node in the tree. So, for example, it will take a document like
the following:</p>

<div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">&lt;style </span><span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">"text/css"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">body</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="nl">font-size</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">12px</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="nt">div</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="nl">height</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="m">2em</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/style&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;body&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"foo"</span><span class="nt">&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</span>

<span class="nt">&lt;/body&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>and turn it into something like:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;body&gt;</code> has a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">font-size</code> of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">12px</code>, everything else is the default</li>
  <li>the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">div</code> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#foo</code> has a computed <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">height</code> of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">24px</code> <sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote">2</a></sup>, everything else is the default. It “inherits” the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">font-size</code> from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&lt;body&gt;</code> as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">12px</code></li>
</ul>

<p>From a code point of view, this means that Stylo takes in Gecko’s C++ DOM tree. It parses all the CSS,
and then runs the cascade on the tree. It stores computed styles on each element in a way that Gecko can read
very cheaply.</p>

<p>Style computation can involve some complex steps that require calling back into C++ code. Servo’s style system
is multithreaded, but Gecko is mostly designed to work off of a single main thread per process, so we need to
deal with this impedence mismatch.</p>

<p>Since the output of Stylo is C++-readable structs, Stylo needs to be able to read and write nontrivial C++
abstractions. Typical FFI involves passing values over a boundary, never to be seen again, however here we’re
dealing with persistent state that is accessed by both sides.</p>

<p>To sum up, we have:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Lots and lots of back-and-forth FFI</li>
  <li>Thread safety concerns</li>
  <li>Rust code regularly dealing with nontrivial C++ abstractions</li>
  <li>A need for nontrivial abstractions to be passed over FFI</li>
</ul>

<p>All of this conspires to make for some really complicated FFI code.</p>

<h1 id="the-actual-techniques">The actual techniques</h1>

<p>I’ll try to structure this so that the more broadly useful (and/or less gnarly) techniques come earlier in the post.</p>

<h2 id="the-basics-of-bindgen">The basics of bindgen</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/rust-lang-nursery/rust-bindgen/">Bindgen</a> is a tool that generates Rust bindings for structs and functions from the provided C or C++ header files. It’s often used for writing Rust bindings to existing C/C++ libraries, however it’s useful for integrations as well.</p>

<p>To use it for an integration, write a header file containing the functions your Rust code needs (referencing structs from other header files if necessary), and <a href="https://rust-lang-nursery.github.io/rust-bindgen/command-line-usage.html">run bindgen on it</a>. For some codebases, doing this once and
checking in the generate file suffices, but if your C++ code is going to change a lot, <a href="https://rust-lang-nursery.github.io/rust-bindgen/tutorial-1.html">run it as a build dependency instead</a>. Beware that this can adversely impact build times, since your Rust build now has a partial
C++ compilation step.</p>

<p>For large C++ codebases, pulling in a single header will likely pull in a <em>lot</em> of stuff. You should <a href="https://rust-lang.github.io/rust-bindgen/allowlisting.html">allowlist</a>, <a href="https://rust-lang.github.io/rust-bindgen/blocklisting.html">blocklist</a>, and/or mark things as <a href="https://rust-lang.github.io/rust-bindgen/opaque.html">opaque</a> to reduce the amount of bindings generated. It’s best to go the allowlisting route — give bindgen an allowlisted list of functions / structs to generate bindings for, and it will transitively generate bindings for any dependencies they may have. Sometimes even this will end up generating a lot, it’s sometimes worth finding structs you’re not using and marking them as opaque so that their bindings aren’t necessary. Marking something as opaque replaces it with an array of the appropriate size and alignment, so from the Rust side it’s just some bits you don’t care about and can’t introspect further.</p>

<p>Bindgen <a href="https://rust-lang-nursery.github.io/rust-bindgen/cpp.html"><em>does</em> support some C++ features</a> (you may need to pass <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-x c++</code>). This is pretty good for generating bindings to e.g. templated structs. However, it’s not possible to support <em>all</em> C++ features here, so you may need to blocklist, opaqueify, or use intermediate types if you have some complicated C++ abstractions in the deps. You’ll typically get an error when generating bindings or when compiling the generated bindings, so don’t worry about this unless that happens.</p>

<p>Bindgen is <em>quite</em> configurable. Stylo has a <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/819cd31a93fd50b7167979607371878c4d6f18e8/servo/components/style/build_gecko.rs">script</a> that consumes a <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/source/layout/style/ServoBindings.toml">large toml file</a> containing all of the configuration.</p>

<h2 id="cbindgen">cbindgen</h2>

<p>We don’t use <a href="https://github.com/eqrion/cbindgen">cbindgen</a> in Stylo, but it’s used for Webrender. It does the inverse of what bindgen does: given a Rust crate, it generates C headers for its public <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">extern "C"</code> API. It’s also quite configurable.</p>

<h2 id="cxx">cxx</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/dtolnay/cxx">cxx</a> is the cool new hotness in 2021, which kind of approaches the problem from both sides, enabling you to write Rust bindings for C++ and C++ bindings for Rust. It’s definitely worth checking out, a lot of the things that are hard to make work with bindgen are trivial in cxx. For example, it automatically figures out what types need to be opaque, it automatically converts between <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&amp;T</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">T*</code> across FFI, and it is overall more targeted for the use case of an FFI layer where Rust and C++ both call each other.</p>

<h2 id="bindgen-aided-c-calling-rust">Bindgen-aided C++ calling Rust</h2>

<p>So bindgen helps with creating things for Rust to call and manipulate, but not in the opposite direction. cbindgen can help here, but I’m not sure if it’s advisable to have <em>both</em> bindgen and cbindgen operating near each other on the same codebase.</p>

<p>In Stylo we use a bit of a hack for this. Firstly, all FFI functions defined in C++ that Rust calls are declared in <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/819cd31a93fd50b7167979607371878c4d6f18e8/layout/style/ServoBindingList.h">one file</a>, and are all named <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Gecko_*</code>. Bindgen supports regexes for things like allowlisting, so this naming scheme makes it easy to deal with.</p>

<p>We also declare the FFI functions defined in Rust that C++ calls in <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/819cd31a93fd50b7167979607371878c4d6f18e8/layout/style/ServoBindingList.h">another file</a>, named <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Servo_*</code>. They’re also all <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/819cd31a93fd50b7167979607371878c4d6f18e8/servo/ports/geckolib/glue.rs">defined in one place</a>.</p>

<p>However, there’s nothing ensuring that the signatures match! If we’re not careful, there may be mismatches, causing bad things to happen at link time or runtime. We use a small <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/819cd31a93fd50b7167979607371878c4d6f18e8/servo/ports/geckolib/tests/build.rs">autogenerated</a> <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/819cd31a93fd50b7167979607371878c4d6f18e8/servo/ports/geckolib/tests/servo_function_signatures.rs">unit test</a> to ensure the validity of the signatures.</p>

<p>This is especially important as we do things like type replacement, and we need tests to ensure that the rug isn’t pulled out from underneath us.</p>

<h2 id="type-replacing-for-fun-and-profit">Type replacing for fun and profit</h2>

<p>Using <a href="https://rust-lang.github.io/rust-bindgen/blocklisting.html">blocklisting</a> in conjunction with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--raw-line</code>/<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">raw_line()</code> flag, one can effectively ask bindgen to “replace” types. Blocklisting asks bindgen not to generate bindings for a type, however bindgen will continue to generate bindings <em>referring</em> to that type if necessary. (Unlike opaque types where bindgen generates an opaque binding for the type and uses it everywhere). <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--raw-line</code> lets you request bindgen to add a line of raw rust code to the file, and such a line can potentially define or import a new version of the type you blocklisted. Effectively, this lets you replace types.</p>

<p>Bindgen generates unit tests ensuring that the layout of your structs is correct (run them!), so if you accidentally replace a type with something incompatible, you will get warnings at the struct level (functions may not warn).</p>

<p>There are various ways this can be used:</p>

<h3 id="safe-references-across-ffi">Safe references across FFI</h3>

<p><em>Note from 2021: <a href="https://github.com/dtolnay/cxx">cxx</a> does this automatically</em></p>

<p>Calling into C++ (and accepting data from C++) is unsafe. However, there’s no reason we should have to worry about this more than we have to. For example, it would be nice if accessor FFI functions – functions which take a foreign object and return something from inside it –  could use lifetimes. It would be even nicer if nullability were represented on the FFI boundary so that you don’t miss null checks, and can assume non-nullness when the C++ API is okay with it.</p>

<p>In Stylo, we have lots of functions like the following:</p>

<div class="language-cpp highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">RawGeckoNodeBorrowedOrNull</span> <span class="nf">Gecko_GetLastChild</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">RawGeckoNodeBorrowed</span> <span class="n">node</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>which bindgen translates to:</p>

<div class="language-rust highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">extern</span> <span class="s">"C"</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">fn</span> <span class="nf">Gecko_GetLastChild</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">RawGeckoNode</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">-&gt;</span> <span class="nb">Option</span><span class="o">&lt;&amp;</span><span class="n">RawGeckoNode</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="p">;</span>   
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Using the <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/819cd31a93fd50b7167979607371878c4d6f18e8/servo/components/style/build_gecko.rs">bindgen build script</a> on a provided <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/819cd31a93fd50b7167979607371878c4d6f18e8/layout/style/ServoBindings.toml#648-671">list of borrow-able types</a>, we’ve told bindgen that:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">FooBorrowedOrNull</code> is actually <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Option&lt;&amp;Foo&gt;</code></li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">FooBorrowed</code> is actually <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&amp;Foo</code></li>
</ul>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Option&lt;&amp;Foo&gt;</code> <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/nomicon/repr-rust.html">is represented as a single nullable pointer in Rust</a>, so this is a clean translation. 
We’re forced to null-check it, but once we do we can safely assume that the reference is valid. Furthermore, due to lifetime elision the actual signature of the FFI function is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">fn Gecko_GetLastChild&lt;'a&gt;(x: &amp;'a RawGeckoNode) -&gt; Option&lt;&amp;'a RawGeckoNode&gt;</code>, which ensures we won’t let the returned reference outlive the passed reference. Lifetime elision means that we can call C++ functions “safely” with the appropriate lifetime requirements, even though C++ has no such concept!</p>

<p>Note that this is shifting some of the safety invariants to the C++ side: We rely on the C++ to give us valid references, and we rely on it to not have nulls when the type is not marked as nullable. Most C++ codebases internally rely on such invariants for safety anyway, so this isn’t much of a stretch.</p>

<p>We do this on both sides, actually: Many of our Rust-defined <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">extern "C"</code> functions that C++ calls get to be internally-safe because the types let us assume the validity of the pointers obtained from C++.</p>

<h3 id="making-c-abstractions-rust-accessible">Making C++ abstractions Rust-accessible</h3>

<p>A very useful thing to do here is to replace various C++ abstractions with Rust versions of them that share semantics. In Gecko, most strings are stored in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nsString</code>/<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nsAString</code>/etc.</p>

<p>We’ve written an <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/6ddb5fb144993fb5de044e2e8d900d7643b98a4d/servo/support/gecko/nsstring/src/lib.rs">nsstring</a> crate that represents layout-compatible <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nsString</code>s in a more Rusty way, with Rusty APIs. We then ask bindgen to replace Gecko <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nsString</code>s with these.</p>

<p>Usually it’s easier to just write an impl for the bindgen-generated abstraction, however sometimes you must replace it:</p>

<ul>
  <li>When the abstraction internally does a lot of template stuff not supported by bindgen</li>
  <li>When you want the code for the abstraction to be in a separate crate</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="potential-pitfall-passing-c-classes-by-value-over-ffi">Potential pitfall: Passing C++ classes by-value over FFI</h2>

<p>It’s quite tempting to do stuff like</p>

<div class="language-cpp highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">RefPtr</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">Foo</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">Servo_Gimme</span><span class="p">(...);</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>where you pass complicated classes by-value over FFI (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefPtr</code> is Gecko’s variant of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Rc&lt;T&gt;</code>/<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Arc&lt;T&gt;</code>).</p>

<p>This works on some systems, but is broken on MSVC:
<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/issues/38258">The ABI for passing non-POD types through functions is different</a>. The linker usually notices this and complains, but it’s worth avoiding this entirely.</p>

<p>In Stylo we handle this by using some macro-generated intermediate types which are basically the same thing as the original class but without any constructors/destructors/operators. We convert to/from these types immediately before/after the FFI call, and on the Rust side we do similar conversions to Rust-compatible abstractions.</p>

<h2 id="sharing-abstractions-with-destructors">Sharing abstractions with destructors</h2>

<p>If you’re passing ownership of collections or other templated types across FFI, you probably want Rust code to be able to destroy C++ objects, and vice versa.</p>

<p>One way of doing this is to implement <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Drop</code> on the generated struct. If you have <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">class MyString</code>, you can do:</p>

<div class="language-cpp highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">MyString</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="c1">// ...</span>
    <span class="o">~</span><span class="n">MyString</span><span class="p">();</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="kt">void</span> <span class="nf">MyString_Destroy</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="n">MyString</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="n">x</span><span class="o">-&gt;~</span><span class="n">MyString</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<div class="language-rust highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">impl</span> <span class="n">Drop</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="nn">bindings</span><span class="p">::</span><span class="n">MyString</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">fn</span> <span class="k">drop</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="k">mut</span> <span class="k">self</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="c">// (bindgen only)</span>
        <span class="nn">bindings</span><span class="p">::</span><span class="nn">MyString</span><span class="p">::</span><span class="nf">destruct</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">self</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="c">// OR</span>
        <span class="nn">bindings</span><span class="p">::</span><span class="nf">MyString_Destroy</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">self</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MyString_Destroy</code> isn’t necessary with bindgen – bindgen will generate a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MyString::destruct()</code> function for you – but be careful, this will make your generated bindings very platform-specific, so be sure to only do this if running them at build time. In general, when bindgen generates C++ <em>methods</em>, your bindings become platform specific and are best regenerated at build time<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote">3</a></sup>.</p>

<p>In Stylo we went down the route of manually defining <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_Destroy()</code> functions since we started off with checked-in platform-agnostic bindings, however we could probably switch to using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">destruct()</code> if we want to now.</p>

<p>When it comes to generic types, it’s a bit trickier, since <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Drop</code> can’t be implemented piecewise on a generic type (you cannot <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">impl Drop for MyVector&lt;Foo&gt;</code>). You have to do something like:</p>

<div class="language-cpp highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">template</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="k">typename</span> <span class="nc">T</span><span class="p">&gt;</span>
<span class="k">class</span> <span class="nc">MyVector</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="c1">// ...</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="c1">// Deallocate buffer, but do not call destructors on elements</span>
<span class="kt">void</span> <span class="nf">MyVector_Deallocate_Buffer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">MyVector</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="kt">void</span><span class="o">&gt;*</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<div class="language-rust highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c">// assume we have an implementation of Iterator for MyVector&lt;T&gt; somewhere</span>

<span class="k">impl</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">T</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">Drop</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="nn">bindings</span><span class="p">::</span><span class="n">MyVector</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">T</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">fn</span> <span class="k">drop</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="k">mut</span> <span class="k">self</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">v</span> <span class="n">in</span> <span class="k">self</span><span class="nf">.iter_mut</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
            <span class="c">// calls the destructor for `v`, if any</span>
            <span class="nn">std</span><span class="p">::</span><span class="nn">ptr</span><span class="p">::</span><span class="nf">drop_in_place</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">v</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="p">}</span>
        <span class="nn">bindings</span><span class="p">::</span><span class="nf">MyVector_Deallocate_Buffer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">self</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="k">mut</span> <span class="n">MyVector</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">T</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="k">mut</span> <span class="n">MyVector</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nb">c_void</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Note that if you forget to add a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Drop</code> implementation for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">T</code>, this will silently forget to clean up the contents of the vector. See <a href="#mirror-types">the next section</a> for some ways to handle this by creating a “safe” mirror type.</p>

<h2 id="mirror-types">Mirror types</h2>

<p>C++ libraries often have useful templated abstractions, and it’s nice to be able to manipulate them from Rust. Sometimes, it’s possible to just tack on semantics on the Rust side (either by adding an implementation or by doing type replacement), but in some cases this is tricky.</p>

<p>For example, Gecko has <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefPtr&lt;T&gt;</code>, which is similar to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Rc&lt;T&gt;</code>, except the actual refcounting logic is up to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">T</code> to implement (it can choose between threadsafe, non-threadsafe, etc), which it does by writing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AddRef()</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Release()</code> methods.</p>

<p>We mirror this in Rust by having a trait:</p>

<div class="language-rust highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c">/// Trait for all objects that have Addref() and Release</span>
<span class="c">/// methods and can be placed inside RefPtr&lt;T&gt;</span>
<span class="k">pub</span> <span class="k">unsafe</span> <span class="k">trait</span> <span class="n">RefCounted</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="c">/// Bump the reference count.</span>
    <span class="k">fn</span> <span class="nf">addref</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="k">self</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="c">/// Decrease the reference count.</span>
    <span class="k">unsafe</span> <span class="k">fn</span> <span class="nf">release</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="k">self</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="c">/// A custom RefPtr implementation to take into account Drop semantics and</span>
<span class="c">/// a bit less-painful memory management.</span>
<span class="k">pub</span> <span class="k">struct</span> <span class="n">RefPtr</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">T</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">RefCounted</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="n">ptr</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="k">mut</span> <span class="n">T</span><span class="p">,</span>
    <span class="mi">_</span><span class="n">marker</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">PhantomData</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">T</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>We implement the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefCounted</code> trait for C++ types that are wrapped in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefPtr</code> which we wish to access through Rust. We have <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/cfaa5a1d48d6bc6552199e73004ecb05d0a9c921/servo/components/style/gecko_bindings/sugar/refptr.rs#258-315">some</a> <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/cfaa5a1d48d6bc6552199e73004ecb05d0a9c921/layout/style/GeckoBindings.h#52-60">macros</a> that make this easier to do. We have to have such a trait, because otherwise Rust code wouldn’t know how to manage various C++ types.</p>

<p>However, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefPtr&lt;T&gt;</code> here can’t be the type that ends up being used in bindgen. Rust doesnt let us do things like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">impl&lt;T: RefCounted&gt; Drop for RefPtr&lt;T&gt;</code> <sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote">4</a></sup>, so we can’t effectively make this work with the bindgen generated type unless we write a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefCounted</code> implementation for every refcounted type that shows up in the bindgen output at all – which would be a lot of work.</p>

<p>Instead, we let bindgen generate its own <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefPtr&lt;T&gt;</code>, called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">structs::RefPtr&lt;T&gt;</code> (all the structs that bindgen generates for Gecko go in a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">structs::</code> module). <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">structs::RefPtr&lt;T&gt;</code> itself doesn’t have enough semantics to be something we can pass around willy-nilly in Rust code without causing leaks. However, it has <a href="https://searchfox.org/mozilla-central/rev/cfaa5a1d48d6bc6552199e73004ecb05d0a9c921/servo/components/style/gecko_bindings/sugar/refptr.rs#150-234">some methods</a> that allow for conversion into the “safe” mirror <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefPtr&lt;T&gt;</code> (but only if <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">T: RefCounted</code>). So if you need to manipulate a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefPtr&lt;T&gt;</code> in a C++ struct somewhere, you immediately use one of the conversion methods to get a safe version of it first, and <em>then</em> do things to it. Refcounted types that don’t have the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefCounted</code> implementation won’t have conversion methods: they may exist in the data you’re manipulating, however you won’t be able to work with them.</p>

<p>In general, whenever attaching extra semantics to generic bindgen types doesn’t work create a mirror type that’s completely safe to use from Rust, with a trait that gates conversion to the mirror type.</p>

<h2 id="potential-pitfall-allocators">Potential pitfall: Allocators</h2>

<p>If you’re passing heap-managed abstractions across FFI, be careful about which code frees which objects. If your Rust
and C++ code don’t share allocators, deallocating memory allocated on the other side can have disastrous consequences.</p>

<p>If you’re building a cdylib or staticlib with Rust (this is likely if you’re linking it with a C++ application), the compiler will by default pick the system allocator (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">malloc</code>), so if your C++ application also uses the same you’re all set.</p>

<p>On some platforms when building rlibs and binaries, Rust may choose jemalloc instead. It’s also possible that your C++ code uses a different allocator (lots of applications use allocators like jemalloc or tcmalloc, some have their own custom allocators like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tor_malloc</code> in Tor).</p>

<p>In such cases you have one of three options:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Avoid transferring ownership of heap-allocated items, only share things as borrowed references</li>
  <li>Call destructors over FFI, as detailed in <a href="#sharing-abstractions-with-destructors">the section on destructors above</a></li>
  <li>Set Rust’s allocator to be the same as documented <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/nightly/std/alloc/#the-global_allocator-attribute">in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">std::alloc</code> module</a>. Basically, can use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#[global_allocator]</code> attribute to select which allocator you wish to use, and if necessary you can implement the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">GlobalAlloc</code> trait on a custom allocator type that calls into whatever custom allocator C++ is using.</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Note from 2021: Most stdlib collections (<a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/nightly/std/vec/struct.Vec.html"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Vec</code></a>, for example) now have an optional “custom allocator” parameter that can be used to swap in a different allocator for a specific use site.</em></p>

<h2 id="arcs-over-ffi-triomphe">Arcs over FFI: Triomphe</h2>

<p>This isn’t really a generalizable technique, but it’s pretty cool and generally instructive, so I’m including it here.</p>

<p>Stylo uses a lot of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Arc</code>s. A <em>lot</em> of them. The entire computation of styles makes heavy use of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Arc::make_mut</code>’s copy-on-write semantics so that we can build up the style tree in parallel but not have to make unnecessary copies of duplicated/defaulted styles for each element.</p>

<p>Many of these <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Arc</code>s need to be readable from C++. Rust’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Arc</code>, however, consists of a pointer to an allocation containing a refcount and the data, so if C++ needs to get access to the data it needs to know the layout of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Arc</code> allocation, which we’d rather not do<sup id="fnref:5" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote">5</a></sup>.</p>

<p>We picked a different route: We created a crate duplicating <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Arc&lt;T&gt;</code> which behaves almost exactly the same as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Arc&lt;T&gt;</code>, but it can be converted to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">OffsetArc&lt;T&gt;</code> which has its pointer point to the <em>middle</em> of the allocation, where the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">T</code> begins. To C++, this just looks like a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">*const T</code>! We were then able to make it work with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefPtr&lt;T&gt;</code> on the C++ side so that C++ can transparently read from the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">OffsetArc&lt;T&gt;</code>, and only needs to call into Rust if it wishes to clone or drop it.</p>

<p>The external version of this crate can be found in <a href="https://docs.rs/triomphe">triomphe</a>. It contains a bunch of other goodies that are additionally useful outside of the FFI world, like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ArcBorrow</code> which is essentially “<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">&amp;Arc&lt;T&gt;</code> without double indirection”, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">UniqueArc&lt;T&gt;</code>, a mutable <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Arc&lt;T&gt;</code> known to be uniquely owned, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ArcUnion&lt;T, U&gt;</code>, which is a space-efficient union of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Arc&lt;T&gt;</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Arc&lt;U&gt;</code>.</p>

<h2 id="other-pitfalls">Other pitfalls</h2>

<h3 id="transparent">Transparent</h3>

<p>It’s <em>very</em> tempting to wrap C++ types in tuple structs and pass them over FFI. For example, one might imagine that the following is okay:</p>

<div class="language-rust highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">struct</span> <span class="nf">Wrapper</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nn">bindings</span><span class="p">::</span><span class="n">SomeCppType</span><span class="p">);</span>

<span class="k">extern</span> <span class="s">"C"</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="c">// C++ signature: `SomeCppType get_cpp_type();`</span>
    <span class="k">fn</span> <span class="nf">get_cpp_type</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="k">-&gt;</span> <span class="n">Wrapper</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This kind of thing is quite useful to get around coherence, or for adding additional semantics to a type.</p>

<p>While there’s basically one obvious way <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Wrapper</code> can be represented, ABI stuff can be tricky, and Rust’s layout isn’t defined. It is safer to use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#[repr(transparent)]</code>, which guarantees that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Wrapper</code> will have the same representation as the type it contains.</p>

<h3 id="c-enums">C enums</h3>

<p>Rust supports C-like enums, but there’s a crucial difference between them. In C, it is not undefined behavior for an enum to have an unlisted value. In fact, the following pattern is not uncommon:</p>

<div class="language-c highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">enum</span> <span class="n">Flags</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="n">Flag1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="n">b0001</span><span class="p">,</span>
    <span class="n">Flag2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="n">b0010</span><span class="p">,</span>
    <span class="n">Flag3</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="n">b0100</span><span class="p">,</span>
    <span class="n">Flag4</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="n">b1000</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">};</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>where the enum is actually used for bitflags, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Flag1 | Flag2</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">0</code> are both valid values for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Flags</code>.</p>

<p>This is not the case in Rust. If you are type-replacing C enums with Rust ones, make sure they are <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#[repr(C)]</code>. The Rust compiler uses invalid enum values as space for packing other information while optimizing types, for example Rust is able to represent <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Option&lt;Option&lt;... 255 times .. Option&lt;bool&gt;&gt;</code> as a single byte.</p>

<p>If you are working with a C enum that is used for bitflags like above, please use an integer type instead. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#[repr(C)]</code> on enums in Rust guarantees layout, but it is <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/stable/nomicon/other-reprs.html">still undefined behavior for any enum to take on invalid values</a>.</p>

<h3 id="abi-concerns">ABI concerns</h3>

<p>ABIs can be tricky. If you <em>just</em> use bindgen with no special flags, you can be pretty much guaranteed to have an okay ABI, but as you start doing type replacements, stuff can get murkier.</p>

<p>Firstly, make sure you’re not passing owned C++ classes with destructors/etc across FFI boundaries. See <a href="#potential-pitfall-passing-c-classes-by-value-over-ffi">above</a> for why. There’s a bunch of subtle stuff here, but you can avoid most of it it if you just don’t pass these things across FFI in an owned way.</p>

<p>Also, try to make sure everything is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#[repr(C)]</code> across the boundary. Rust’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">improper-ctypes</code> lints will help here.</p>

<h2 id="should-c-apis-be-unconditionally-unsafe">Should C++ APIs be unconditionally <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unsafe</code>?</h2>

<p>Before I get into this, I want to reiterate that most of the recommendations in this post are for <em>complex</em> C++-Rust integrations, which are likely to only crop up when attempting to rewrite parts of a large C++ codebase in Rust. Such codebases have unique needs and it’s important to calibrate for that when judging what’s right for them.</p>

<p>I recall when <a href="https://www.chromium.org/Home/chromium-security/memory-safety/rust-and-c-interoperability">this Chromium post</a> and <a href="https://steveklabnik.com/writing/the-cxx-debate">Steve’s <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cxx</code> post</a> came out, there was a bunch of discussion about C++ functions not being universally marked <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unsafe</code>. Essentially, a lot of people are of the opinion that all FFI into C++ (or C) should be unconditionally marked <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unsafe</code> (and that tools like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cxx</code> should follow these rules).</p>

<p>Back then I wrote <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/rust/comments/ielvxu/the_cxx_debate/g2jurb3/?context=3">a Reddit comment</a> about my thoughts on this. It’s a comment that’s the length of a blog post in and of itself so I’m not going to reproduce all of it here, but I’ll try to get the gist. I highly suggest you read it instead of this section.</p>

<p>In short, I would recommend people in large, complex codebases doing heavy C++ interop to generally be okay with marking functions calling into C++ as “safe” provided that function would be considered “safe to call without thinking too much about it” on the C++ side, whatever that means for your codebase.</p>

<p>From <a href="https://manishearth.github.io/blog/2017/12/24/undefined-vs-unsafe-in-rust/">my post on “undefined” vs “unsafe”</a>, for Rust I define “safe” as</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Basically, in Rust a bit of code is “safe” if it cannot exhibit undefined behavior under all circumstances of that code being used.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>C++ doesn’t have a rigid language-level concept of safety that can be applied the same way. Instead, most C++ code follows a similar heuristic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>a bit of code is “safe” if it cannot exhibit undefined behavior under all <strong>expected</strong> circumstances of that code being used.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is, perhaps, not as good or useful a heuristic as the one we have for Rust, but it’s still a heuristic that gets used in deciding how careful one needs to be when using various APIs. After all, there are <em>plenty</em> of giant C++ codebases out there, they have got to be able to reason about safety <em>somehow</em>.</p>

<p>When you decide to meld together a C++ and Rust codebase, or start rewriting parts of a C++ codebase in Rust, you have already in essence decided for a large part of the codebase to not exactly follow Rust’s safety rules (but hopefully still be safe). There is little to be gained by making that an explicit part of your FFI boundary. Rather, it is more useful to save <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unsafe</code> on the FFI boundary for truly unsafe functions which you actually do need to be careful to call.</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unsafe</code> is useful for finding potential sources of badness in your codebase. For a tightly-integrated Rust/C++ codebase it’s already well known that the C++-side is introducing badness, marking every simple C++ getter as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unsafe</code> will lead to alarm fatigue and make it <em>harder</em> to find the real problems.</p>

<p>It’s worth figuring out where this boundary lies for you. Tools like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cxx</code> make it straightforward to call C++ functions through a safe interface, and it’s valuable to make use of that support.</p>

<h2 id="closing-comments">Closing comments</h2>

<p>Again, before going down this route it’s worth wondering if you <em>really</em> need tight Rust-C++ integration. When possible, it’s always better to pick a small, well-defined API boundary, rather than Stylo-esque tight integration with shared objects and a highly criscrossed callgraph.</p>

<p>These days <a href="https://github.com/dtolnay/cxx">cxx</a> is probably the most complete tool for such integrations. <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang-nursery/rust-bindgen/">bindgen</a> and <a href="https://github.com/eqrion/cbindgen">cbindgen</a> are still quite good, but cxx is C++-first, with a lot more magic, and generally seems to Just Work without too much configuration.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/google/autocxx">autocxx</a> is a cool concept by Adrian Taylor which melds bindgen and cxx to make something even <em>more</em> magical. It’s currently experimental, but I’m going to be watching it with interest.</p>

<p>Overall the field of Rust and C++ integration is at a stage where it’s mature enough for integrations to be <em>possible</em> without too much effort, but there are still tons of ways things could be improved and I’m super excited to see that happen as more people work on such integrations!</p>

<p><em>Thanks to Adam Perry, Adrian Taylor, katie martin, Nika Layzell, and Tyler Mandry for reviewing drafts of this post</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>The <em>cascade</em> in “Cascading Style Sheets” is the process used to take all the potential rules which could apply to an element and find the “most applicable” one that gets actually used. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">em</code> unit is font-size-relative, so <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">2em</code> with a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">font-size</code> of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">12px</code> is computed to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">2 * 12 = 24px</code>. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>C++ name mangling <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Name_mangling#How_different_compilers_mangle_the_same_functions">is not standardized</a>, so any function with the C++ ABI will generate a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#[link_name = "_Z1foobarbaz"]</code> attribute on the Rust side, and the exact string used here will differ across compiler implementations and platforms. Since GCC and Clang follow the same scheme, most people will encounter this problem when their code doesn’t work on Windows due to MSVC using a different scheme. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Drop</code> impls are restricted in a bunch of ways for safety, in particular you cannot write <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">impl&lt;T: RefCounted&gt; Drop for RefPtr&lt;T&gt;</code> unless <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefPtr</code> is defined as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RefPtr&lt;T: RefCounted&gt;</code>. It’s not possible to have a generic type that has an impl of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Drop</code> for only <em>some</em> possible instantiations of its generics. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Rust’s standard library does not typically guarantee anything about the layout of its types, and furthermore, Rust does not make many guarantees about the stability of most types without a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#[repr]</code> attribute. This would <em>work</em>, but it would be brittle and prone to breakage. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adventures in Systems Programming: C++ Local Statics]]></title>
    <link href="http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2015/06/26/adventures-in-systems-programming-c-plus-plus-local-statics/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://manishearth.github.io/blog/2015/06/26/adventures-in-systems-programming-c-plus-plus-local-statics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a while now I’ve been quite interested in compilers and systems programming in general; and I
feel that an important feature of systems programming is that it’s relatively easy to figure out
what a line of code does (modulo optimizations) at the OS or hardware level<sup id="fnref:5" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote">1</a></sup>. Conversely, it’s
important to know how your tools work more than ever in systems programming. So when I see a
language feature I’m not familiar with, I’m interested in finding out how it works under the hood.</p>

<p>I’m not a C++ expert. I can work on C++ codebases, but I’m not anywhere near knowing all of the
features and nuances of C++. However, I am pretty good at Rust and understand a decent portion of
the compiler internals. This gives me a great perspective — I’ve not yet internalized most C++
features to take them for granted, and I’m well equipped to investigate these features.</p>

<p>Today I came across some C++ code similar to the following<sup id="fnref:0" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:0" class="footnote">2</a></sup>:</p>

<div class="language-cpp highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kt">void</span> <span class="nf">foo</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">static</span> <span class="n">SomeType</span> <span class="n">bar</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Env</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">-&gt;</span><span class="n">someMethod</span><span class="p">();</span>
    <span class="k">static</span> <span class="n">OtherType</span> <span class="n">baz</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Env</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">-&gt;</span><span class="n">otherMethod</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">bar</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This code piqued my interest. Specifically, the local <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">static</code> stuff. I knew that when you have a
static like</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>static int FOO = 1;
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1</code> is stored somewhere in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.data</code> section of the program. This is easily verified with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">gdb</code>:</p>

<div class="language-cpp highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">static</span> <span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">THING</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mh">0xAAAA</span><span class="p">;</span>

<span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
 <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

</code></pre></div></div>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>$ g++ test.cpp -g
$ gdb a.out
(gdb) info addr THING
Symbol "THING" is static storage at address 0x601038.
(gdb) info symbol 0x601038
THING in section .data
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This is basically a part of the compiled program as it is loaded into memory.</p>

<p>Similarly, when you have a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">static</code> that is initialized with a function, it’s stored in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.bss</code>
section, and initialized before <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main()</code>. Again, easily verified:</p>

<div class="language-cpp highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="cp">#include&lt;iostream&gt;
</span><span class="k">using</span> <span class="k">namespace</span> <span class="n">std</span><span class="p">;</span>

<span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">bar</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
 <span class="n">cout</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="s">"bar called</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
 <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mh">0xFAFAFA</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="k">static</span> <span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">THING</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">bar</span><span class="p">();</span>

<span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
 <span class="n">cout</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="s">"main called</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
 <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

</code></pre></div></div>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>$ ./a.out 
bar called
main called
$ gdb a.out
(gdb) info addr THING
Symbol "THING" is static storage at address 0x601198.
(gdb) info symbol 0x601198
THING in section .bss
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>We can also leave statics uninitialized (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">static int THING;</code>) and they will be placed in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.bss</code><sup id="fnref:8" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote">3</a></sup>.</p>

<p>So far so good.</p>

<p>Now back to the original snippet:</p>

<div class="language-cpp highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kt">void</span> <span class="nf">foo</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">static</span> <span class="n">SomeType</span> <span class="n">bar</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Env</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">-&gt;</span><span class="n">someMethod</span><span class="p">();</span>
    <span class="k">static</span> <span class="n">OtherType</span> <span class="n">baz</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Env</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">-&gt;</span><span class="n">otherMethod</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">bar</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Naïvely one might say that these are statics which are scoped locally to avoid name clashes. It’s
not much different from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">static THING = bar()</code> aside from the fact that it isn’t a global
identifier.</p>

<p>However, this isn’t the case. What tipped me off was that this called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Env()</code>, and I wasn’t so sure
that the environment was guaranteed to be properly initialized and available before <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main()</code> is
called <sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">4</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Instead, these are statics which are initialized the first time the function is called.</p>

<div class="language-cpp highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="cp">#include&lt;iostream&gt;
</span><span class="k">using</span> <span class="k">namespace</span> <span class="n">std</span><span class="p">;</span>

<span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">bar</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
 <span class="n">cout</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="s">"bar called</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
 <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mh">0xFAFAFA</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="kt">void</span> <span class="nf">foo</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
 <span class="n">cout</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="s">"foo called</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
 <span class="k">static</span> <span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">bar</span><span class="p">();</span>
 <span class="n">cout</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="s">"Static is:"</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="n">i</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
 <span class="n">cout</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="s">"main called</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
 <span class="n">foo</span><span class="p">();</span>
 <span class="n">foo</span><span class="p">();</span>
 <span class="n">foo</span><span class="p">();</span>
 <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>$ g++ test.cpp
$ ./a.out
main called
foo called
bar called
Static is:16448250
foo called
Static is:16448250
foo called
Static is:16448250
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Wait, “the first time the function is called”? <em>Alarm bells go off…</em> Surely there’s some cost to that! Let’s investigate.</p>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>$ gdb a.out
(gdb) disas bar
   // snip
   0x0000000000400c72 &lt;+15&gt;:    test   %al,%al
   0x0000000000400c74 &lt;+17&gt;:    jne    0x400ca4 &lt;_Z3foov+65&gt;
   0x0000000000400c76 &lt;+19&gt;:    mov    $0x6021f8,%edi
   0x0000000000400c7b &lt;+24&gt;:    callq  0x400a00 &lt;__cxa_guard_acquire@plt&gt;
   0x0000000000400c80 &lt;+29&gt;:    test   %eax,%eax
   0x0000000000400c82 &lt;+31&gt;:    setne  %al
   0x0000000000400c85 &lt;+34&gt;:    test   %al,%al
   0x0000000000400c87 &lt;+36&gt;:    je     0x400ca4 &lt;_Z3foov+65&gt;
   0x0000000000400c89 &lt;+38&gt;:    mov    $0x0,%r12d
   0x0000000000400c8f &lt;+44&gt;:    callq  0x400c06 &lt;_Z3barv&gt;
   0x0000000000400c94 &lt;+49&gt;:    mov    %eax,0x201566(%rip)        # 0x602200 &lt;_ZZ3foovE1i&gt;
   0x0000000000400c9a &lt;+55&gt;:    mov    $0x6021f8,%edi
   0x0000000000400c9f &lt;+60&gt;:    callq  0x400a80 &lt;__cxa_guard_release@plt&gt;
   0x0000000000400ca4 &lt;+65&gt;:    mov    0x201556(%rip),%eax        # 0x602200 &lt;_ZZ3foovE1i&gt;
   0x0000000000400caa &lt;+71&gt;:    mov    %eax,%esi
   0x0000000000400cac &lt;+73&gt;:    mov    $0x6020c0,%edi
   // snip
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The instruction at <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">+44</code> calls <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bar()</code>, and it seems to be surrounded by calls to some <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__cxa_guard</code>
functions.</p>

<p>We can take a naïve guess at what this does: It probably just sets a hidden static flag on
initialization which ensures that it only runs once.</p>

<p>Of course, the actual solution isn’t as simple. It needs to avoid data races, handle errors, and
somehow take care of recursive initialization.</p>

<p>Let’s look at the <a href="http://mentorembedded.github.io/cxx-abi/abi.html#once-ctor">spec</a> and one <a href="http://www.opensource.apple.com/source/libcppabi/libcppabi-14/src/cxa_guard.cxx">implementation</a>, found by searching for
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__cxa_guard</code>.</p>

<p>Both of them show us the generated code for initializing things like local statics:</p>

<div class="language-cpp highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">obj_guard</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">first_byte</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span> <span class="n">__cxa_guard_acquire</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">obj_guard</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="k">try</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="c1">// ... initialize the object ...;</span>
      <span class="p">}</span> <span class="k">catch</span> <span class="p">(...)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="n">__cxa_guard_abort</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">obj_guard</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="k">throw</span><span class="p">;</span>
      <span class="p">}</span>
      <span class="c1">// ... queue object destructor with __cxa_atexit() ...;</span>
      <span class="n">__cxa_guard_release</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="n">obj_guard</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">obj_guard</code> is our “hidden static flag”, with some other extra data.</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__cxa_guard_acquire</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__cxa_guard_release</code> acquire and release a lock to prevent recursive
initialization. So this program will crash:</p>

<div class="language-cpp highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="cp">#include&lt;iostream&gt;
</span><span class="k">using</span> <span class="k">namespace</span> <span class="n">std</span><span class="p">;</span>

<span class="kt">void</span> <span class="nf">foo</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">bool</span> <span class="n">recur</span><span class="p">);</span>

<span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">bar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">bool</span> <span class="n">recur</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
 <span class="n">cout</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="s">"bar called</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
 <span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">recur</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="n">foo</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">false</span><span class="p">);</span>
 <span class="p">}</span>
 <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mh">0xFAFAFA</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="kt">void</span> <span class="nf">foo</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kt">bool</span> <span class="n">recur</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
 <span class="n">cout</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="s">"foo called</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
 <span class="k">static</span> <span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">bar</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">recur</span><span class="p">);</span>
 <span class="n">cout</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="s">"Static is:"</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span> <span class="n">i</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>



<span class="kt">int</span> <span class="nf">main</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
 <span class="n">foo</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">true</span><span class="p">);</span>
 <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<div class="language-text highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>$ g++ test.cpp
$ ./a.out 
foo called
bar called
foo called
terminate called after throwing an instance of '__gnu_cxx::recursive_init_error'
  what():  std::exception
Aborted (core dumped)
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Over here, to initialize <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">i</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bar()</code> needs to be called, but <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bar()</code> calls <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">foo()</code> which needs <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">i</code>
to be initialized, which again will call <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bar()</code> (though this time it won’t recurse). If <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">i</code> wasn’t
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">static</code> it would be fine, but now we have two calls trying to initialize <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">i</code>, and it’s unclear as
to which value should be used.</p>

<p>The implementation is pretty interesting. Before looking at the code my quick guess was that the
following would happen for local statics:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">obj_guard</code> is a struct containing a mutex and a flag with three states:
“uninitialized”, “initializing”, and “initialized”. Alternatively, use an atomic state indicator.</li>
  <li>When we try to initialize for the first time, the mutex is locked, the flag is set
to “initializing”, the mutex is released, the value is initialized, and the flag is set to “initialized”.</li>
  <li>If when acquiring the mutex, the value is “initialized”, don’t initialize again</li>
  <li>If when acquiring the mutex, the value is “initializing”, throw some exception</li>
</ul>

<p>(We need the tristate flag because without it recursion would cause deadlocks)</p>

<p>I suppose that this implementation would work, though it’s not the one being used. The
<a href="https://github.com/android/platform_bionic/blob/master/libc/bionic/__cxa_guard.cpp">implementation in bionic</a> (the Android version of the C stdlib) is similar; it
uses per-static atomics which indicate various states. However, it does not throw an exception when
we have a recursive initialization, it instead seems to deadlock<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote">5</a></sup>. This is okay because the C++
spec says (<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/open/n2356/stmt.html#stmt.dcl">Section 6.7.4</a>)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If control re-enters the declaration (recursively) while the object is being initialized, the
behavior is undefined.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>However, the implementations in <a href="https://github.com/gcc-mirror/gcc/blob/master/libstdc%2B%2B-v3/libsupc%2B%2B/guard.cc">gcc/libstdc++</a> (also <a href="http://www.opensource.apple.com/source/libcppabi/libcppabi-14/src/cxa_guard.cxx">this version</a> of
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">libcppabi</code> from Apple, which is a bit more readable) do something different. They use a global
recursive mutex to handle reentrancy. Recursive mutexes basically can be locked multiple times by a
single thread, but cannot be locked by another thread till the locking thread unlocks them the same
number of times. This means that recursion/reentrancy won’t cause deadlocks, but we still have one-
thread-at-a-time access. What these implementations do is:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">guard_object</code> is a set of two flags, one which indicates if the static is initialized,
and one which indicates that the static is being initialized (“in use”)</li>
  <li>If the object is initialized, do nothing (this doesn’t use mutexes and is cheap).
This isn’t exactly part of the implementation in the library, but is part of the generated code.</li>
  <li>If it isn’t initialized, acquire the global recursive lock</li>
  <li>If the object is initialized by the time the lock was acquired, unlock and return</li>
  <li>If not, check if the static is being initialized from the second <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">guard_object</code> flag. If it is
“in use”, throw an exception.</li>
  <li>If it wasn’t, mark the second flag of the static’s guard object as being “in use”</li>
  <li>Call the initialization function, bubble errors</li>
  <li>Unlock the global mutex</li>
  <li>Mark the second flag as “not in use”</li>
</ul>

<p>At any one time, only one thread will be in the process of running initialization routines, due to
the global recursive mutex. Since the mutex is recursive, a function (eg <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bar()</code>) used for
initializing local statics may itself use (different) local statics. Due to the “in use” flag, the
initialization of a local static may not recursively call its parent function without causing an
error.</p>

<p>This doesn’t need per-static atomics, and doesn’t deadlock, however it has the cost of a global
mutex which is called at most once per local static. In a highly threaded situation with lots of
such statics, one might want to reevaluate directly using local statics.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/llvm-mirror/libcxxabi/blob/master/src/cxa_guard.cpp#L188">LLVM’s libcxxabi</a> is similar to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">libstdc++</code> implementation, but instead of a recursive
mutex it uses a regular mutex (on non-ARM Apple systems) which is unlocked before
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__cxa_guard_acquire</code> exits and tests for reentrancy by noting the thread ID in the guard object
instead of the “in use” flag. Condvars are used for waiting for a thread to stop using an object. On
other platforms, it seems to deadlock, though I’m not sure.</p>

<p>So here we have a rather innocent-looking feature that has some hidden costs and pitfalls. But now I
can look at a line of code where this feature is being used, and have a good idea of what’s
happening there. One step closer to being a better systems programmer!</p>

<p><em>Thanks to Rohan Prinja, Eduard Burtescu, and Nishant Sunny for reviewing drafts of this blog post</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Emphasis on <em>relatively</em>. This article will show that it’s definitely not “easy” all the time. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:0" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>This was JNI code which obtained a JNI environment and pulled out method/class IDs from it to be used later <a href="#fnref:0" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:8" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Unless it has a constructor or otherwise isn’t made out of trivially constructible types; in this case it is treated similar to the previous case. <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I checked later, and it was indeed the case that global statics are initialized before <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Env()</code> is ready <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I later verified this with a modification of the crashing program above stuck inside some JNI Android code. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
